<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="out/NauticalLexiconODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Nautical Lexicon Project Standoff Markup for Bibliographic References</title>
                <editor role="creator">Claire Zak</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information - multilingual glossary of nautical terms</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This project is based on 3x5 index cards of glossary information and notes which
                    have been transcribed</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <standOff>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abell1948">Abell, W. 1948. The Shipwright’s Tale. Cambridge: Cambridge University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abrate1957">Abrate, M. 1957. “Creta, Colonia Veneziana nei Secoli XIII - XV.” Economia e
                Storia 4: 251-77.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abulafia1974">Abulafia, D. 1974. “Corneto-Tarquinia and the Italian Mercantile republics: the
                earliest evidence.” Papers of the British School at Rome 42: 224-34.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abulafia1976">Abulafia, D. 1976. “Dalmation Ragusa and the Norman Kingdom of Sicily.” Slavonic
                &amp; East European Review 54: 412-28.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abulafia1291">Abulafia, D. 1980. “Marseilles, Acre and the Mediterranean, 1200-1291.” In Coinage
                in the Latin East: The Fourth Oxford Symposium on Coinage and Monetary History,
                edited by P.W. Edbury and D.M. Metcalf, 19-39.Oxford: BAR International
                Series.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abulafia1980">Abulafia, D. 1980. “Venice and the Kingdom of Naples in the Last Years of Robert
                the Wise 1332-1343.” Papers of the British School at Rome 48: 186-204.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abulafia1370">Abulafia, D. 1981. “Southern Italy and the Florentine economy, 1265-1370.”
                Economic History Review 33: 377-88.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Abulafia1983">Abulafia, D. 1983. “The Crown and the Economy under Roger II and His Successors.”
                Dumbarton Oaks Papers 37: 1-14.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abulafia1983">Abulafia, D. 1983. “Sul Commercio del Grano Siciliano nel Tardo Duecento.” In La
                società mediterranea all'epoca del Vespro: XI Congresso di Storia della Corona
                d'Aragona, Palermo-Trapani-Erice, 23-30 aprile 1982, 5-22. Palermo: Accademia di
                Scienze, Lettere e Arti.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abulafia1173">Abulafia, D. 1984. “Ancona, Byzantium and the Adriatic, 1155-1173.” Papers of the
                British School at Rome 52: 195-216.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abulafia1300">Abulafia, D. 1985. “Catalan Merchants and the Western Mediterranean, 1236-1300:
                Studies in the Notarial Acts of Barcelona and Sicily.” Viator 16: 209-42.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abulafia1400">Abulafia, D. 1987. Italy, Sicily and the Mediterranean, 1100-1400. UK: Variorum
                Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Abulafia1500">Abulafia, D. 1993. Commerce and Conquest in the Mediterranean, 1100–1500. London:
                Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Adelson1960">Adelson, H.L. 1960. “Early medieval trade routes.” American Historical Review 65:
                271-87.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Adler1907">Adler, M.N., ed. 1907. The Itinerary of Benjamin of Tudela. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ahrweiler1966">Ahrweiler, H. 1966. Byzance et la Mer: La Marine de Guerre, la Politique et Les
                Institutions Maritimes de Byzance aux VIIe–XVe Siècles. Paris: Presses
                Universitaires de France.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Aistleitner1963">Aistleitner, J. 1963. Wörterbuch der ugaritischen Sprache. Berlin: Akademie
                Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Akdikmen1992">Akdikmen, R. 1992. Langenscheidt's Pocket Turkish Dictionary. Berlin:
                Langenscheidt.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Alighieri1966">Alighieri, D. 1966. The Divine Comedy. Translated by L. Biancolli. New York:
                Washington Square Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Alberti, S. Diccionari Mitjà Castellà-Català, Català-Castellà.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Albion1926">Albion, R.G. 1926. Forests and Sea Power. Cambridge: Harvard University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Albion1972">Albion, R.G. 1972. Naval and Maritime History: An Annotated Bibliography. 4th ed.
                Connecticut: Mystic Seaport Museum.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Antoni1930">Antoni, M., A.M. Alcover, and F. de B. Moll. 1930-62. Diccionari
                Català-Valencià-Balear, 10 vols.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Alt1945">Alt, A. 1945. Ägyptisch-Ugaritisches. Archiv für Orientforschung 15: 69-74.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Amades1924">Amades, J., &amp; Roig, E. 1924. “Vocabulari de l’Art de la Navegació i la Pesca.”
                Bulletí de Dialectología Catalana 12: 1-115.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Amargier1990a">Amargier, P. 1990. “Enquête Bibliographique Relative à la Façade Provençale du
                Bord Méditerranéen” Miège, J. 1990. Navigation et Migrations en Méditerranée: De la
                Préhistoire à Nos Jours, p. 41-96.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Amargier1990b">Amargier, Paul 1990 “La Vie Quotidienne d'un Chantier Naval Sur l'Étang de Bages
                et de Sigeant en 1319” in Miège, J. 1990. Navigation et Migrations en Méditerranée:
                De la Préhistoire à Nos Jours, p. 251-65.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Amit1962">Amit, M. 1962. “The Sailors of the Athenian fleet.” Athenaeum 60: 157-78.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Anderson1445">Anderson, R.C. 1925. “Italian Naval Architecture about 1445.” Mariner’s Mirror 11:
                135-63.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Anderson1295">Anderson, R.C. 1928. “English Galleys in 1295.” Mariner’s Mirror 14:
                220-41.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Anderson1945">Anderson, R.C. 1945. “Jal’s ‘Memoire No. 5’ and the manuscript ‘Fabbrica di
                Galere.’” Mariner’s Mirror 31: 160-67.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Anderson1962">Anderson, R.C. 1962. Oared Fighting Ships: From Classical Times To The Coming of
                Steam. London: Argus Books.</bibl>
            <bibl>André, J. 1964. “La Résine et la Poiz Dans l’Antiquité, Technique et
                Terminologie.” L’Antiquité Classique 33: 86-97.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Andriotes1951">Andriotes, N. 1951. ‘Ετυμολογικὸ Λεξικὸ τῡς Κοινῡς Νεοελλυνικῡς [Etymological
                Dictionary Of Standard Modern Greek]. 1st ed. Thessaloniki: Institute of Modern
                Greek Studies.</bibl>
            <bibl>Anonymous. 1370. Libre del Consolat de Mar [Book of the Consulate of the
                Sea].</bibl>
            <bibl>Anonymous. 1830. Dictionnaire de la Langue Franque ou Petit Mauresque, Suivi de
                Quelques Dialogues Familiers et d'un Vocabulaire de Mots Arabes les Plus Usuels; à
                l'Usage des Français en Afrique. Marseilles.</bibl>
            <bibl>Anonymous. 1904.Liber Statutorum Civitatis Ragusii Compositus Anno 1272: Monumenta
                Historico-Juridica Slavorum Meridionalium, edited by V. Bogisic and C. Jirecek.
                Zagreb: Jugoslavenska Akademiya Zanosti i Umjetnosti.</bibl>
            <bibl>Anonymous. 1959. Bollettino dell'Atlante Linguistico Mediterraneo, edited by Mirko
                Deanovic. Florence</bibl>
            <bibl>Anonymous. 1972. Underwater Archaeology: a Nascent Discipline. Paris, UNESCO,
                Museums and Monuments 13.</bibl>
            <bibl>Anonymous. 1974. “Les Grandes Escales Maritimes.” Recueils de la Société
                Jean-Brodin. Brussels: Rougé.</bibl>
            <bibl>Anonymous. 1986. L'Exploitation de la Mer: Vol. 1: La Mer, Moyen d'Échange et de
                Communication. Antibes.</bibl>
            <bibl>Anonymous. 1987. Spanish-English-Spanish Naval Dictionary. New York.</bibl>
            <bibl>Anonymous. 1989. A Comprehensive Maritime Dictionary. Arab Maritime
                Academy.</bibl>
            <bibl> Anonymous. 1990. Navigations Et Migrations En Méditerranée De La Préhistoire À
                Nos Jours. Paris: Editions du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique.</bibl>
            <bibl>Antoniadis-Bibicou, H. 1966. Etudes d’Histoire Maritime de Byzance: a Propos du
                ‘Thème des Caravisiens’. Paris: S. E. V. P. E. N.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Applebaum1976a">Applebaum, S. 1976. “Economic life in Palestine.” In The Jewish People in the
                First Century, Volume 2, edited by S. Safrai, M. Stern, D. Flusser, and W.C. van
                Unnik, 631-700. Leiden: Brill.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Applebaum1976b">Applebaum, S. 1976. “The Social And Economic Status Of The Jews In The Diaspora.”
                In The Jewish People In The First Century. Historical Geography, Political History,
                Social, Cultural and Religious Life and Institutions, edited by S. Safrai and S.
                Brunner, 701-27. Assen, Drenthe: Royal Van Gorcum.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Arbil1989">Arbil, B., B. Hamilton, and D. Jacoby, ed. 1989. Latins and Greeks in the
                Mediterranean After 1204. London: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Archibald1978">Archibald, L. 1978. The Sea and Medieval Civilization. London: Variorum
                Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Arkell1959">Arkell, A.J. 1959. “Early Shipping in Egypt.” Antiquity 33: 52-53.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ash1945">Ash, H.B., ed. 1945. Res Rustica, by Lucius Junius Moderatus Columella. Translated
                by H.B. Ash, Loeb Classical Library Series. Cambridge: Harvard University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ashburner1909">Ashburner, W. 1909. Nomos Rodion Nautikos: The Rhodian Sea-Law. Oxford: Clarendon
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ashtor1970a">Ashtor, E. 1970. “Quelques Observations d’un Orientaliste Sur la Thèse de
                Pirenne.” Journal of the Economic and Social History of the Orient 13:
                166-94.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ashtor1970b">Ashtor, E. 1970. “Nouvelles Réflexions Sur la thèse de Pirenne.” Revue suisse
                d'histoire 20: 601-07.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ashtor1974">Ashtor, E. 1974. “The Venetian Supremacy in Levantine Trade: Monopoly or
                Pre-Colonialism?” Journal of European Economic History 3: 5-53.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ashtor1976a">Ashtor, E. 1976. “Observations on Venetian Trade in the Levant in the XIVth
                Century.” Journal of European Economic History 5: 533-86.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ashtor1976b">Ashtor, E. 1976. A Social and Economic History of the Near East in the Middle
                Ages. Los Angeles: University of California Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ashtor1977">Ashtor, E. 1977. “Aperçus sur les Radhanites.” Revue suisse d'histoire 27:
                245-75.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ashtor1978">Ashtor, E. 1978. Studies on the Levantine Trade in the Middle Ages: Collected
                Studies Series 74. London: Variorum Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ashtor1984">Ashtor, E. 1984. “The Wheat Supply of the Mamlūk Kingdom." Asian and African
                Studies: Journal of the Israel Oriental Society 18: 283-95.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ashtor1986">Ashtor, E. 1986. East-West Trade in the Medieval Mediterranean. Edited by B.Z.
                Ḳedar. London: Variorum Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Astour1970">Astour, M.C. 1970. “Maʾḫadu, the Harbor of Ugarit.” Journal of the Economic and
                Social History of the Orient 13: 113-27.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Astour1973">Astour, M.C. 1973. “Ugarit and the Aegean.” Alter Orient und Altes Testament 22:
                17-27.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Austin1970">Austin, M.M. 1970. Greece and Egypt in the Archaic Age. Cambridge: Cambridge
                Philological Society.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Austin1981">Austin, M.M., and P. Vidal-Naquet. 1981. Economic and Social History of Ancient
                Greece: An Introduction. Los Angeles: University of California Press.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Avienus1934">Avienus, L.F. Ora Maritima. Edited by R. Berthelot, 1934. Paris: Librairie
                Ancienne Honore Champion.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Avrameas1985">Avrameas, A. 1985. “Maps of the Aegean.” In Maps and Mapmakers of the Aegean,
                edited by V. Sphyroeras, A. Avramea, and S. Asdrahas, 22-32. Athens: Olkos.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bagrow1964">Bagrow, L. 1964. History of Cartography: Revised and Enlarged by R. A. Skelton.
                London: C.A. Watts.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bakker1987">Bakker, P. 1987. “A Basque Nautical Pidgin: A Missing Link in the History of FU.”
                Journal of Pidgin and Creole Languages 2.1: 1–30.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bakker1988">Bakker, P. 1988. “Basque Pidgin Vocabulary in European-Algonquian Trade Contacts.”
                In Papers of the Nineteenth Algonquian Conference, edited by W. Cowan, 7-15. Ottawa:
                Carleton University.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Balard1973">Balard, M. 1973. Gênes et l'Outre-Mer: I. Les Actes de Caffa du Notaire Lamberto
                di Sambuceto, 1289-1290. Paris-La Haye: Mouton &amp; Co.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Balard1978">Balard, M. 1978. La Romanie Génoise (XIIe-début du XVe Siècle), 2 vol. Gênes-Rome:
                Bibliothèque des Écoles françaises d’Athènes et de Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Balard1981">Balard, M. 1981. “Les Équipage des Flottes Génoises au Xive Siècle,” in Le Genti
                del Mare Mediterraneo, edited by R. Ragosta, 511-534. Naples: L. Pironti.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Balard1994">Balard, M. 1994. “Coastal Shipping and Navigation in the Mediterranean, Cogs,
                Caravels and Galleons: the Sailing Ship 1000-1650.” In Conway’s History of the Ship,
                edited by R. Gardiner, 131-138. London: Naval Institute Press. Balsan, L. 1951.
                “L'industrie de la Résine Dans les Causses et Son Extension dans l'Empire Romain.”
                Gallia 9: 53-55.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Balsdon1979">Balsdon, J.P.V.D. 1979. Romans and Aliens. Chapel Hill: University of North
                Carolina Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bamford1700">Bamford, P.W. 1965. “Slaves for the Galleys of France, 1665-1700.” In Merchants
                and Scholars, in Merchants and Scholars, edited by J. Parker, 171-91. Minneapolis:
                University of Minnesota.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bamford1973">Bamford, P.W. 1973. Fighting Ships and Prisons - The Mediterranean Galleys of
                France in the Age of Louis XIV. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Barker1966">Barker, J.W. 1966. Justinian and the Later Roman Empire. Madison: University of
                Wisconsin Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Barnett1958">Barnett, R.D. 1958. “Early Shipping in the Near East.” Antiquity 32:
                220-30.</bibl>
            <bibl>Barras de la Penne, J. A. de. 1697. La Science des Galères Qui Renferme Tout Ce
                Qui Regarde la Construction, l’Armement, la Manæuvre, le Combat et la Navigation des
                Galères. Paris: Musée de la Manche.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Basch1978">Basch, L. 1978. “Le Navire mnš et Autres Notes de Voyage en Égypte.” Mariner’s
                Mirror 64: 99-123.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Basch1986">Basch, L. 1986. “Note Sur le Calfatage: la Chose et le Mot.” Archæonautica 6:
                187-98.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bass1972a">Bass, G. F. 1972. A History of Seafaring: Based on Underwater Archaeology. NY:
                Walker and Co.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bass1972b">Bass, G. F. 1972. “The Earliest Seafarers in the Mediterranean and the Near East.”
                In A History of Seafaring: Based on Underwater Archaeology, edited by G.F. Bass,
                11-36. NY: Walker and Co.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bass1985">Bass, G. F. 1986. “A Bronze Age Shipwreck at Ulu Burun (Kaș): 1985 Campaign.”
                American Journal of Archaeology 90: 269-96.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bass1987">Bass, G. F. 1987. “Oldest Known Shipwreck Reveals Splendors of the Bronze Age.”
                National Geographic Research 172.6: 692-733.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bass1990">Bass, G. F. 1990. “Nautical Archaeology and Biblical Archaeology.” Biblical
                Archaeologist 53.1: 4-12.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bass1986">Bass, G. F., et al. 1989. “The Bronze Age Shipwreck at Ulu Burun: 1986 Campaign.”
                American Journal of Archaeology 93: 1-29.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bass1982">Bass, G. F., and F. van Doorninck, Jr. 1982. Yassi Ada: Volume I, a
                Seventh-Century Byzantine Shipwreck. College Station: Texas A&amp;M University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Bastard de Péré, R. 1972. “Navires Méditerranéens du Temps de Saint Louis.” Revue
                d’Histoire Économique et Sociale 50: 327-56.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bathe1978">Bathe, B., and A. Villiers. 1978. The Visual Encyclopedia of Nautical Terms Under
                Sail. New York: Crown Publishing Group.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bautier1955">Bautier, A.-M. 1955. “ Contributions à un Vocabulaire Économique du Midi de la
                France.” Archivum Latinitatis Medii Aevi 25: 5-28.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bautier1992">Bautier, R.-H. 1992. Commerce Méditerranéen et Banquiers Italiens au Moyen Âge.
                London: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Beglinger1958">Beglinger, E. 1958. “Distillation of Resinous Wood.” USDA Forest Service
                Laboratory Report 496.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Belgrano1901">Belgrano, L.T., and C. Imperiali. 1901. Annali Genovesi di Caffaro e de'suoi
                Continuatori. Genoa and Rome.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Bell1948">Bell, H. I. 1948. Egypt, from Alexander the Great to the Arab Conquest: A Study
                in the Diffusion and Decay of Hellenism. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bellabarba1986">Bellabarba, S. 1986. “Ballirunia and Ballinvernia.” Mariner’s Mirror 72:
                476-77.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Bellabarba1988">Bellabarba, S. 1988. “The Square-rigged Ship of the Fabrica di galere MS.”
                Mariner’s Mirror 74: 225-39.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bembo1497">Bembo, M. 1497-82.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bembo1482">Bembo, M. 1482-84.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bengtson1969">Bengtson, H. 1969. The Greeks and the Persians: From the Sixth to the Fourth
                Centuries. London: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson.</bibl>
            <bibl>Ben Jonah (of Tudela), B. 1575. Itinerarium Benjamini Tudelensis. Antwerp:
                Christophe Plantin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Benson1979">Benson, M. 1979. An English-Serbocroatian Dictionary. Philadelphia: University of
                Pennsylvania Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Best1980">Best, J. G., and N.M. de Vries, eds. 1980-82. Interaction and Acculturation in the
                Mediterranean. 2 vols. Amsterdam: B.R. Grüner.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Biddlecombe2012">Biddlecombe, G. 1848. rev. 2012. The Art of Rigging. Mineola: Dover
                Publications.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bill1994">Bill, Jan. 1994. “Ship Construction: Tools and Techniques.” In Cogs, Caravels and
                Galleons: The Sailing Ship 1000-1650, edited by R. Unger, 151-59. London: Robert
                Gardiner.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Billingmeier1977">Billingmeier, J.-Chr. 1977. “Origin of the Greek word Phoinix.” Talanta:
                Proceedings of the Dutch Archaeological and Historical Society 8-9: 1-4.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bischoff1989">Bischoff, B. 1989. Latin Paleography: Antiquity and the Middle Ages.
                Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Blackman1982">Blackman, D.J. 1982. “Ancient Harbours in the Mediterranean.” International
                Journal of Nautical Archaeology and Underwater Exploration 11: 79-104,
                185-211.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Blancard1884">Blancard, L. 1884-5. Documents Inédits Sur le Commerce de Marseille au Moyen-Âge.
                2 vols. Marseilles.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Boardman1980">Boardman, J. 1980. The Greeks Overseas. London: Thames &amp; Hudson.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Boerio1856">Boerio, G. 1856. Dizionario del Dialetto Veneziano. Venice: Reale Tipografia di G.
                Cecchini.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Boggs1946">Boggs, R.S., L. Kasten, H. Keniston, and H. B. Richardson 1946. Tentative
                Dictionary of Medieval Spanish. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Boislisle, A., ed. 1872. “Informationes Civitatis Massiliae pro Passagio
                Transmarino.” Annales School and British Social History 9.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bonfante1941">Bonfante, G. 1941. “The name of the Phoenicians.” Classical Philology 36:
                1-20.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bonino1978">Bonino, M. 1978. “Lateen-rigged Medieval Ships.” International Journal of Nautical
                Archaeology and Underwater Exploration 7: 9-15.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bordone1537">Bordone, B. 1537. Isolario…</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Borghesi1976">Borghesi, V. 1976. Il Mediterraneo Tra Due Rivoluzioni Nautiche (Secoli XIV-XVII).
                Florence: La Nuova Italia Editrice.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Borsari1963">Borsari, S. 1963. Il Dominio Veneziano a Creta nel XIII Secolo. Naples: University
                of Naples.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Borsari1964">Borsari, S. 1964. “Il Commercio Veneziano dell’Impero Bizantino Nel XII Secolo.”
                Revista Storia Italiana 76: 985-86.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Boudy1948">Boudy, P. 1948-58. Economie Forestière Nord-Africaine. 4 vols. Paris:
                Laros.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bouzek1985">Bouzek, J. 1985. The Aegean, Anatolia and Europe: Cultural Interrelations in the
                Second Millennium B.C. Göteborg: P. Åströms förlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bowersock1983">Bowersock, G.W. 1983. Roman Arabia. Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bowman1986">Bowman, A.K. 1986. Egypt After the Pharaohs 332 BC-AD 642: From Alexander to the
                Arab Conquest. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bowman1948">Bowman, R.A. 1948. “Arameans, Aramaic and the Bible.” Journal of Near Eastern
                Studies 7: 65-90.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bragadin1951">Bragadin, M. 1951. Repubbliche Italiane sul Mare. Milan: Aldo Garzanti Ed.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Brand1204">Brand, C.M. 1968. Byzantium Confronts the West 1180-1204. Cambridge: Harvard
                University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Brand1984">Brand, C.M. 1984. “The Fourth Crusade: Some Recent Interpretations.” Medievalia et
                Humanistica 12: 33-45.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Branigan1969">Branigan, J.J., and H.R. Jarrett. 1969. The Mediterranean Lands. London: Macdonald
                &amp; Evans.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bratianu1929">Bratianu, G.I. 1929. Recherches Sur le Commerce Génois dans la Mer Noire au XIIIe
                Siècle. Paris: Librairie Orientaliste Paul Geuthner.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bratianu1967">Bratianu, G.I. 1967. La mer Noire: Des origines à la Conquête Ottomane. (Acta
                Historica, Number 9). Munich: Societas Academica Dacoromana.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Braun1572">Braun, G., and F. Hogenberg. 1572. Civitates Orbis Terrarum. Cologne.</bibl>
            <bibl>Braun-Blanquet, J., and J. Susplugas. 1937. “Reconnaissance Phytogéographique dans
                les Corbières.” Bulletin de la Société Botanique de France 84.5: 669-85.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bravo1983">Bravo, B. 1983. “Le Commerce de Céréales Chez les Grec de l'Époque Archaïque.” In
                Trade and Famine in Classical Antiquity, edited by P. Garnsey and C. R. Whittaker,
                17-29. Cambridge: Cambridge Philological Society.</bibl>
            <bibl>Bréard, C. 1894. “Le Compte du Slos des galées de Rouen au XIVe Siècle
                (1382-1384).” Bibliothèque de l'École des chartes 55: 158-60.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Brito Rebello, J. I., ed. 1903. O Livro de Marinharia. Lisbon.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Broch1981">Broch, I., and E.H. Jahr. 1981. Russenorsk et Pidginspråk i Norge. Oslo:
                Novus.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Broch1927">Broch, O. 1927. “Russenorsk.” Archiv für slavische Philologie 41: 209-62.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Broodbank1989">Broodbank, C. 1989. “The Longboat and Society in the Cyclades in the Keros-Syros
                culture.” American Journal of Archaeology 93.3: 319-37.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Brown1920">Brown, H.F. 1920. “The Venetians and the Venetian Quarter in Constantinople to the
                Close of the Twelfth Century.” Journal of Hellenic Studies 40: 68-70.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Browning1983">Browning, R. 1983. Medieval and Modern Greek. Cambridge: Cambridge University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Brunot1920">Brunot, L. 1920. Notes Lexicologiques sur le Vocabulaire Maritime de Rabat &amp;
                Salé. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Library.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Brunt1974">Brunt, A. ed. 1974. The Roman Economy: Studies in Ancient Economic and
                Administrative History. Oxford: Blackwell.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bucks1949">Bucks, C.D. 1949. A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European
                Languages. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bunbury1923">Bunbury, H.M. 1923. The Destructive Distillation of Wood. London: Benn.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Burn1984">Burn, A.R. 1984. Persia and the Greeks: The Defence of the West, c. 546-478 B.C..
                London: Edward Arnold.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Burns1980">Burns, R.I. 1980. “Piracy as an Islamic-Christian Interface in the Thirteenth
                Century.” Viator 11: 165-78.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Byrne1920">Byrne, E.H. 1920. “Genoese Trade with Syria in the Twelfth Century.” American
                Historical Review 25: 191-219.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Byrne1930">Byrne, E.H. 1930. Genoese Shipping in the Twelfth and Thirteenth Centuries.
                Cambridge: Medieval Academy of America.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cadogan1986">Cadogan, G. ed. 1986. The End of the Early Bronze Age in the Aegean. Leiden:
                Brill.</bibl>
            <bibl>Caffarus. Liber Annalium Genuensis Reipublicae Inceptus ab Anno de 1100 Usque ad
                Annum 1293.</bibl>
            <bibl>du Cange, C. F. 1688. Glossarium ad Scriptores Mediae et Infimae Graecitatis. 2
                vols. Lyon.</bibl>
            <bibl>du Cange, C. F. 1883-1887. Glossarium Mediae et Infimae Latinitatis. L. Favre,
                ed., 9 vols. Niortt.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cameron1993">Cameron, A. 1993. The Mediterranean World in Late Antiquity. London:
                Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Campbell1500">Campbell, T. 1987. “Portolan Charts from the Late Thirteenth Century to 1500.” In The History of Cartography, Volume One: Cartography in Prehistoric, Ancient, and
                Medieval Europe and the Mediterranean, edited by J. B. Harley and D. Woodward.
                Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Camus1936a">Camus, A. 1936. Les Chênes: Monographie du Genre Quercus.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Camus1936-38a">Camus, A. 1936-38. Encyclopédie Économique de Sylviculture, Volume Six:
                Sous-genre Cyclobalanopsis, edited by P. Lechevalier. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Camus1936-38b">Camus, A. 1936-38. “Quercus Cerris.” In Encyclopédie Économique de Sylviculture, Volume Six: Sous-genre Euquercus, edited by P. Lechevalier. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Camus1936-38c">Camus, A. 1936-38. “Quercus Mesobalanus.” In Encyclopédie Économique de
                Sylviculture, Volume Six: Sous-genre Euquercus, edited by P. Lechevalier.
                Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Camus1936b">Camus, A. 1936. Encyclopédie Économique de Sylviculture, Volume Seven: Sous-genre Lepidobalanus, edited by P. Lechevalier. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cano1611a">Cano, T. 1611. Arte Para Fabricar, Fortificar, y Apareiar Naos de Guerra, y
                Merchante, edited by E. Luys. Seville.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cano1611b">Cano, T. 1611. Arte Para Fabricar y Aparejar Naos, edited by E. M. Dorta. Canary Islands.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Campany, A. 1779. Memorias Historicas sobre la Marina Commercio y Artes de la
                Antigua Ciudad de Barcelona, edited by A. Sanelia, reedited by E. Giralt y Raventos
                and C. Batille y Gallart (1962). 5 vols. Madrid.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cappelli1961">Cappelli, A. 1912 (1961). Lexicon Abbreviaturarum: Dizionario Di Abbreviature Latine ed Italiane. Milan.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Caracausi1983">Caracausi, G. 1983. “Arabismi Medievali di Sicilia.” Supplementi al Bollettino de
                Centro di Studi Filologici e Linguistici Siciliani 5. Palermo.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Carson1962">Carson, R.A.G. 1962. Coins of the World. New York: Harper.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Carbonell1963">Carbonell, P., and M. A. Tavares. 1963. A Terminologia Naval Portuguesa Anterior a
                1460. Lisbon.</bibl>
            <bibl> Carpine-Lancre, J. 1990. “Documentation et Histoire Maritime,” in Anon.,
                Navigations Et Migrations En Méditerranée De La Préhistoire À Nos Jours, p.
                11-17.</bibl>
            <bibl>Carrère, C. 1967. Barcelone, Centre Économique à la Époque des Difficultés
                (1380-1462). Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cary1929">Cary, M., and E. H. Warmington. 1929. The Ancient Explorers. London: Methuen and
                Co, Ltd.</bibl>
            <bibl>de las Casas, B. 1552. Historia de las Indias, second ed., edited by A. M. Carlo
                and L. Hanke (1965). Mexico City: Fondo de Cultura Económica.</bibl>
            <bibl>Càssola, F. 1972. Romani e Italici in Oriente.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Casson1950">Casson, L. 1950. “The Isis and Her Voyage.” Transactions of the American
                Philological Association 81: 43-56.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Casson1954">Casson, L. 1954. “The Grain Trade of the Hellenistic World.” Transactions of the
                American Philological Association 85: 168-87.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Casson1964">Casson, L. 1964. The Ancient Mariners: Seafarers and Sea Fighters of the
                Mediterranean in Ancient Times. New York: MacMillan.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Casson1971">Casson, L. 1971. Ships and Seamanship in the Ancient World. Princeton.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Casson1975">Casson, L. 1975. “Bronze Age Ships: the Evidence of the Thera Wall Paintings.”
                Journal of Nautical Archaeology and Underwater Exploration 4: 3-10.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Casson1979">Casson, L. 1979. “Traders and Trading in Classical Athens.” Expedition 21:
                25-32.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Casson1985">Casson, L. 1985. ”Greek and Roman Shipbuilding: New Findings.” The American
                Neptune 45: 10-19.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Casson1989">Casson, L. 1989. Periplus Maris Erythræi. Princeton.</bibl>
            <bibl>Castellani-Pollidori, O. 1957. “I Più Antichi Grecismi Nautici in Latino.” Atti e
                Memorie dell’Accademia Toscana 22: 183-264.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cejador y Frauca, J. 1929. Vocabulario Medieval Castellano. Hildesheim: Georg Olms
                Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Chadwick1969">Chadwick, J. 1969. “Greek and Pre-Greek.” Transactions of the American
                Philological Society 68.1: 80-98. Chantraine, P. 1928. “Sur le Vocabulaire Maritime
                des Grecs.” In Étrennes de Linguistiques Offertes à Émile Benveniste, 1-25.
                Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Charanis1959">Charanis, P. 1959. “Ethnic Changes in the Byzantine Empire in the Seventh
                Century.” Dumbarton Oaks Papers 13: 23-44.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Charanis1973">Charanis, P. 1973. Social, Economic and Political Life in the Byzantine Empire.
                London.</bibl>
            <bibl>Charles-Picard, G. and C. Charles-Picard. 1961. Daily Life in Carthage at the Time
                of Hannibal. Translated by A.E. Foster. New York: MacMillan.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Charlesworth1926">Charlesworth, M. P. 1926. Trade-Routes and Commerce of the Roman Empire.
                London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Chaytor1933">Chaytor, H. J. 1933. A History of Aragon and Catalonia. London: Methuen &amp;
                Co.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cheetham1981">Cheetham, N. 1981. Mediaeval Greece. New Haven: Yale.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Chiat1988">Chiat, M. J. and K. L. Reyerson. 1988. The Medieval Mediterranean: Cross-Cultural
                Contacts.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Christides1982">Christides, V. 1982. “Two Parallel Naval Guides of the Tenth Century: Qudama's
                Document and Leo VI's Naumachica: A Study on Byzantine and Moslem Naval
                Preparedness.” Graeco-Arabica 1: 51-103.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Christides1984">Christides, V. 1984. “Naval Warfare in the Eastern Mediterranean (6th-14th
                centuries): an Arabic Translation of Leo VI's Naumachica.” Graeco-Arabica 3:
                137-48.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Christopoulos1974">Christopoulos, G. A. 1974. History of the Hellenic World: Prehistory and
                Protohistory to 1100 B.C. University Park: Pennsylvania State University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Christol1971">Christol, M. 1971. “Remarques sur les Naviculaires d'Arles.” Latomus 30:
                643-63.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Cipolla1956">Cipolla, C.M. 1956. Money, Prices and Civilization in the Mediterranean World.
                Princeton University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Citarella1967">Citarella, A.O. 1967. “The Relations of Amalfi with the Arab World Before the
                Crusades.” Speculum 42: 299-312.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Citarella1968">Citarella, A.O. 1968. “Patterns in Medieval Trade: the Commerce of Amalfi Before
                the Crusades.” Journal of Eastern History 28: 531-55.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Coates1993">Coates, J. 1993. “The Naval Architecture of European Oared Ships.” The Royal
                Institution of Naval Architects, Spring Meetings 1993, Paper 9.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Coates1971">Coates, W.A. 1971. “The Lingua Franca.” In Proceedings of 5th Kansas Linguistics
                Conference, edited by F. Ingemann, 25-34. Lawrence: University of Kansas.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cohen1970">Cohen, D. 1970. Dictionnaire des Racines Sémitiques ou Attestées dans les Langues
                Sémitiques. Paris-La Haye: Mouton.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cohen1973">Cohen, E. E. 1973. Ancient Athenian Maritime Courts. Princeton.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cohn1926">Cohn, W. 1926. Die Geschichte der Sizilischen Flotte unter der Regierung
                Friedrichs II. Sicily.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Coldstream1982">Coldstream, J.N. 1982. “Greeks and Phoenicians in the Aegean.” In Phönizier im
                Westen, edited by H.G. Niemeyer, 261-75. Mainz: Philip von Zabern.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Collier1976">Collier, B. 1976. “On the origins of Lingua Franca.” Journal of Creole Studies 1:
                281-98.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Conway1934">Conway, R. S., et al. 1934. The Pre-Italic Dialects of Italy. Massachusetts:
                Cambridge.,,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cook1962">Cook, J. M., 1962. The Greeks in Ionia and the East. New York: Frederick A.
                Praeger, Inc.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Coopland1962">Coopland, G.W. 1962. “A Glimpse of the Late Fourteenth Century Ships and
                Shipping.” Mariner’s Mirror 48: 186-92.</bibl>
            <bibl>Corazzini di Bulciano, F. 1900-07 Vocabolario Nautico Italiano. 7 vols.
                Florence.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Corominas1948">Corominas, J. 1948. “The Origin of the Spanish Ferreruelo, Ital. Ferraiuolo, and
                the Importance of the Study of Lingua Franca for Romance Etymology.” Publications of
                the Modern Language Association 63: 719-726.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Corominas1973">Corominas, J. 1973. Breve Diccionario Etimológico de la Lengua Castellana. 3d. ed.
                Madrid: Editorial Gredos.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Corominas1980">Corominas, J. 1980. Diccionari Etimològic i Complementari de la Llengua Catalana.
                Barcelona: Curial/La Caixa.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Corominas1984">Corominas, J. and J. A. Pascual. 1981-1984. Diccionario Crítico Etimológico
                Castellano e Hispánico. Madrid: Gredos.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cortelazzo1970">Cortelazzo, M. 1970. L'Influsso Greco a Venezia. Bologna: Casa Editrice Profesor
                Riccardo Patron.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cortelazzo1974">Cortelazzo, M. 1974. “I Rapporti Linguistici Tra Venezia E La Grecia Prima Della
                Caduta Di Constantinopli,” in A. Pertusi, ed., Venezia e il Levante Fino al Secolo
                XV, vol. 2, 136-7. Florence.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cortelazzo1979a">Cortelazzo, M., ed. 1979. Guida ai Dialetti Veneti. Cooperativa Libraria Editrice
                Degli Studenti dell'Università di Padova.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cortelazzo1979b">Cortelazzo, M. and P. Zolli. 1979. Dizionario Etimologico della Lingua Italiana. 5
                vols. Bologna: Zanichelli</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Craigie1983">Craigie, P. C. 1983. Ugarit and the Old Testament. Grand Rapids: W. B. Eerdmans
                Publishing Company.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Crescentio1602">Crescentio, B. R. 1602. Nautica Mediterranea. Rome: Appresso Bartolomeo
                Bonfadino.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Culican1966">Culican, W. 1966. The First Merchant Venturers. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cunlife1924">Cunlife, R. J. 1924. A Lexicon of the Homeric Dialect. London: Blackie &amp;
                Son.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Cuntz1905">Cuntz, O. 1905. Der Stadiasmus Maris Magni- Texte und Untersuchungen.,</bibl>
            <bibl> D'Albertis, E. A. 1893. Le Costruzioni Navali e l'arte della Navigazione al Tempo
                di Cristoforo Colombo. Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="D'Arms1974">D’Arms, J. H. 1974. “Puteoli in the Second Century of the Roman Empire: a Social
                and Economic Study.” The Journal of Roman Studies 64:104.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="D'Arms1980">D’Arms, J. H., and E. C. Kopff. 1980. “The Seaborne Commerce of Ancient Rome:
                Studies in Archaeology and History.” In Memoirs of the American Academy in Rome 36
                Rome: American Academy in Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dain1943">Dain, A. 1943. Naumachica. Paris: Les Belles Lettres.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Davies1986">Davies, A. M. 1986. “The Linguistic Evidence: Is There Any?.” In The end of the
                Early Bronze Age in the Aegean, edited by G. Cadogan, 93-123. Leiden: Brill.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Davis1991">Davis, R. C. 1991. Shipbuilders of the Venetian Arsenal: Workers and Workplace in
                the Preindustrial City 22 (0-8018-4095-3) 256. Baltimore: John Hopkins University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Davis1980">Davis, W. H. 1980. Greek Papyri of the First Century. Chicago: Ares
                Publication.</bibl>
            <bibl>Deanović, M. 1937. “Concordanze nella terminologia marinara del Mediterraneo.”
                Archivum Romanicum 21: 269-283.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Debrunner1969">Debrunner, A., and A. Scherer. 1969. Geschichte der griechischen Sprache. Berlin:
                De Gruyter.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Deen1937">Deen, N. G. H. 1937. Glossaria duo Vasco-Islandica. Amsterdam: H. J. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Delatte1946">Delatte, A. 1946. “L'Armement d'une Caravelle Grecque du XVIe Siècle d'Après un
                Manuscrit de Vienne.” Miscellanea Giovanni mercati 2: 490-508.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Delatte1947a">Delatte, A. 1947. Les Portulans grecs 1 vol. 1. Liège-Paris: Bibliothèque de la
                Faculté de Philosophie et Lettres de l'Université de Liège.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Delatte1947b">Delatte, A. 1947. Les Portulans Grecs. 2 vol. Liège-Paris: Académie Royale de
                Belqique.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Delatte1958">Delatte, A. 1958. Les Portulans Grecs. 2 vol. Brussels: Académie Royale de
                Belqique.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dell1967">Dell, H. J. 1967. The Origin and Nature of Illyrian Piracy. Historia 16:
                344-358.</bibl>
            <bibl>Dell’Orco, P. 1981. “On Humanities, Ankoina, Chalinos.” International Journal of
                Nautical Archaeology and Underwater Exploration 10: 66-71.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Desborough1972">Desborough, V. R. d’A. 1972. The Greek Dark Ages. New York: St. Martin’s
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Denoix1953">Denoix, L. 1953. Les Connaissances Nautiques de Rabelais. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Descoendres1989">Descoendres, J. -P., ed. 1989. “Greek Colonists and Native Populations.”
                Proceedings of the First Australian Congress of Classical Archaeology July 1985:
                9-14.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Devoto1968">Devoto, G. 1968. Avviamento alla Etimolgia Italiana. Florence: Le Monnier Diez de
                Games.,</bibl>
            <bibl> Diez de Games, G. 1940. “El Victorial: Crónica de Don Pero Niño,” J. de Mata
                Carriazo, ed. Colección de Crónicas Españolas, I. Madrid.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dittenberger1927">Dittenberger, W. 1927. “Foreign Groups in Rome during the First Centuries of the
                Empire.” G. La Piana, trans. Harvard Theological Review 20: 383-403.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dopp1420">Dopp, P. -H. 1958. Traité d'Emmanuel Piloti sur le Passage en Terre Sainte (1420).
                Louvain: Université de Louvain.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dossin1939">Dossin, G. 1939. “Les Archives Economiques du Palais de Mari.” Syria 20:
                97-113.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dossin1970">Dossin, G. 1970. “La Route de l’Étain en Mésopotamie au Temps de Zimri-Lim.” Revue
                d’Assyriologie et d'Archéologie Orientale 64: 97-106.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dotson1979">Dotson, J. E. 1979. “Merchant and Naval Influences on Galley Design at Venice and
                Genoa in the Fourteenth Century,” in C. L. Symonds, ed., New Aspects of Naval
                History: Selected Papers Presented at the Fourth Naval History Symposium.
                Annapolis.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dotson1650">Dotson, J. E. 1994. “Treatises on Shipbuilding before 1650,” in R. W. Unger, ed.,
                Cogs, Caravels and Galleons - The Sailing Ship 1000-1650, 160-168.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Doumas1983">Doumas, C. G. 1983. Thera, Pompeii of the Ancient Aegean: Excavations at Akrotiri
                1967-1979. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Drews1988">Drews, R. 1988. The Coming of the Greeks. Princeton University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dufourcq1966">Dufourcq, C. -E. 1966. L'Espagne Catalane et le Maghreb aux XIIIe et XIVe Siècles.
                Paris: Librairie Hachette.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dufourcq1975">Dufourcq, C. -E. 1975. La Vie Quotidienne dans les Ports Méditerranéens au Moyen
                Age. Paris: Librairie Hachette.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dufourcq1981">Dufourcq, C. -E. 1981. “Le Équipages Catalans au XIVe Siècles: Effectifs,
                Composition, Enrolement, Paye, Vie à Bord,” in Le Genti del Mare Mediterraneo
                535-559.</bibl>
            <bibl>Duncan-Jones, R. P. 1974. The Economy of the Roman Empire. Cambridge University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Duncan-Jones, R. P. 1977. “Giant Cargo Ships in Antiquity.” Classical Quarterly
                27: 331-332.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dunn1987">Dunn, O. C., and J. E. Kelley, Jr. 1987. The Diario of Christopher Columbus' First
                Voyage to America: 1492-1493. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Edler1934">Edler, F. 1934. Glossary of Medieval Terms of Business. Cambridge: The Medieval
                Academy of America, Kraus Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Edward1973">Edward, I. E. S., et. al., eds. 1973. The Cambridge Ancient History: Volume I,
                Part I: History of the Middle East and the Aegean Region Circa 1800-1380 B.C.
                Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Eickhoff1966">Eickhoff, E. 1966. Seekrieg und Seepolitik Zwischen Islam und Abendland: das
                Mittelmeer unter Byzantinischer und Arabischer Hegemonie 650-1040. Berlin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Eiseman1987">Eiseman, C. J., and Ridgway, B. S. 1987. The Porticello Shipwreck, a Mediterranean
                Merchant Vessel of 415-385 B.C. Texas A&amp;M University: Institute of Nautical
                Archaeology.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Elcock1960">Elcock, W.D. 1960. The Romance Languages. London: Faber &amp; Faber, Ltd.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Emanuele1977">Emanuele, P. D. 1977. “Ancient Square Rigging, With and Without Lifts.”
                International Journal of Nautical Archaeology 6: 181-185.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Emberger1930">Emberger, M. L. 1930. “La Végétation de la Région Méditerranéenne.” Revue Générale
                de Botanique 42: 705-721.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Entwistle1962">Entwistle, W. J. 1962. The Spanish Language, Together with Portuguese, Catalan and
                Basque. London: Faber &amp; Faber, Ltd.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ericsson1984">Ericsson, C.H. 1984. Navis Oneraria. Åbo.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Ernout1932">Ernout, A., and A. Meillet. 1932. Dictionnaire Étymologique de la Langue Latine.
                Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl>Evelyn-White, H. G., trans. 1914. Hesiod, the Homeric Hymns and Homerica.
                Cambridge: Loeb Library, Harvard University.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fahmy1966">Fahmy, A. M. 1966. Muslim Naval Organization in the Eastern Mediterranean, From
                the Seventh to the Tenth century A.D. 2d. ed., Cairo: National Publication &amp;
                Printing House.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Falconer1780">Falconer, W. 1780. An Universal Dictionary of the Marine. London.</bibl>
            <bibl>Farrère, C. 1962. Histoire de la Marine Française. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fennis1978">Fennis, J. 1978. La "Stolonomie" et Son Vocabulaire Maritime Marseillais: Edition
                Critique d’un Manuscrit du XVIe Siècle et Étude Historique Philologique et
                Etymologique des Terms de Marines Levantins. Amsterdam: Holland Univeristy
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fensham1967">Fensham, F. C. 1967. “Shipwreck in Ugarit and Ancient Near Eastern Law Codes.”
                Oriens Antiquus 6: 221-224.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ferguson1959">Ferguson, C. A. 1959. “The Arabic Koiné.” Language 35: 616-630.</bibl>
            <bibl>Fernández Duro, C. 1881. Tratado de la Galafatería y Carena de las Naos, y en la
                Forma que Se Debe Hacer: De Unos Documentos Nauticos Titulados- Tratados Varios
                Manuscritos y Aquí Hechos Encuadernar por Juan Anotnio Rico de Mata el Año de 1689.
                Llagut.</bibl>
            <bibl>Fernández Duro, C., ed. 1876-1881. Disquisiciones Náuticas. 6 vols. Madrid:
                Sucesores de Rivadeneyra.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fernandes1616">Fernandes, M. 1616. Livro das Traças de Carpintaria. Lisbon: Library of
                Ajuda.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ferrand1924">Ferrand, C. 1924. “L'Element Persan dans les Textes Nautiques Arabes des XVe et
                XVIe Siècles.” Journal Asiatique, April-June 1924: 193-257.</bibl>
            <bibl>Festus, Sextus Pompeius. On the Meaning of Words [Abridgment of the Lost Glossary
                of Marcus Verrius Flaccus, fl. 20 B.C.]. L. Teubner, ed. 1913.</bibl>
            <bibl>Février, J. G. 1950. “L’ancien Marine Phénicien.” La Nouvelle Clio 3: 128.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Filangieri1981">Filangieri, R., ed. 1950-1981. I Registri della Cancellaria Angioina. 33 vols.
                Naples.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fincati1877">Fincati, L. 1877. Vocabulario Nautico Inglese-Italiano e Italiano-Inglese.
                Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Finley1935">Finley, M. I. 1935. “Emperors, Naukleros and Kapelos.” Classical Philology 30:
                320-336.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Finley1979a">Finley, M. I. 1979. The History of Sicily: Ancient Sicily to the Arab Conquest.
                London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Finley1979b">Finley, M. I. 1979. The World of Odysseus. New York: Pelican.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Finley1981">Finley, M. I. 1981. Economy and Society in Ancient Greece. New York:
                Penguin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fisher1985">Fisher, E. A. 1985. “The Trade Patterns of the Mycenaeans in Southern Italy.”
                American Journal of Archaeology 89: 330.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fitzgerald1985">Fitzgerald, M. A. 1985. “The Ship,” in Oleson, J. P., The Small Finds and the
                Ship: Volume II of the Harbours of Cæsarea Maritima: Results of the Caesarea Ancient
                Harbour Excavation Project, 1980-1985. Oxford: BAR International Series.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fitzgerald1989">Fitzgerald, M. A. 1989. “A Roman Merchant Ship at Caesarea Maritima, Israel.”
                Insitute of Nautical Archaeology Quarterly 16, No. 2: 4-9.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fitzgerald1990">Fitzgerald, M. A. 1990. “The Ship of Saint Paul, Part II: Comparative Archæology.”
                Biblical Archaeologist 53, No. 1: 31-45.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fitzmyer1970">Fitzmyer, J. A. 1970. “The Languages of Palestine in the First Century A.D.”
                Catholic Bible Quarterly 32: 501-531.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Folena1970">Folena, G. 1968-1970. “Introduzione al Veneziano ‘de là da mar.” Bolletino
                dell’Atlante Linguistico Mediterraneo 10-11: 331-376.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Foley1981">Foley, V., and W. Soedel. 1981. “Ancient Oared Warships.” Scientific American 244,
                No. 4: 148-163.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fontenay1982">Fontenay, M. 1980-1982. “Chiourmes Turques au XVIIe Siècle,” in Le Genti del Mare
                Mediterraneo, edited by R. Ragosta, 877-903.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Forbes1967">Forbes, R. J. 1967. Bergbau, Steinbruchtatigkeit und Hüttenwesen. Archaeologia
                Homerica.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Foucher1957">Foucher, L. 1957. Navires et Barques: Figures Sur des Mosaiques Découvertes a
                Sousse et Aux Environs. Tunis.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fourquin1990">Fourquin, N. 1990. “Les Galères de Narbonne,” in Navigations et Migrations en
                Méditerranée de la Préhistoire à Nos Jours. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fourquin1994">Fourquin, N., and P. Rigaud.1994. De la Nave au Pointu. St. Tropez/Toulon:
                Objectif Mer et Capian Méditerranée.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Foxhall1982">Foxhall, L., and H. A. Forbes. 1982. “Sitometreia: the Role of Grain as a Staple
                Food in Classical Antiquity.” Chrion 12: 41-90.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Frabetti1983">Frabetti, P. 1983. Portolan Charts: Carte Nautiche Italiane. West Orange: Saifer
                Publishing.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fraenkel1886">Fraenkel, S. 1886. Die Aramäischen Fremdwörter im Arabischen. Leyden.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Frank1916">Frank, T. 1916. “Race Mixture in the Roman Empire.” American Historical Review 21:
                689-708.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Frank1933">Frank, T., ed., 1933-40. An Economic Survey of Ancient Rome. 5 vols.
                Baltimore.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Frank1937">Frank, T. 1937. “Notes on Roman commerce.” Journal of Roman Studies 27: 72.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Frank1962">Frank, T. 1962. An Economic History of Rome. New York.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Franklin1978">Franklin, A. D., et. al. 1978. The Search for Ancient Tin: Papers from a Seminar.
                Washington: Smithsonian.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Friel1994">Friel, I. 1994. “The Carrack: the Advent of the Full Rigged Ship,” in R. W. Unger,
                ed., Cogs, Caravels and Galleons - The Sailing Ship 1000-1650, 77-90.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Fronzaroli1955">Fronzaroli, P. 1955. “Nota Sulla Formazione della Lingua Franca.” Atti e Memorie
                dell'Accademia Toscana di Scienze e Lettere "La Colombaria" 20: 212-252.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fronzaroli1966">Fronzaroli, P. 1966-7. “Il Mare e i Corsi d'Acqua nel Lessico Comune Semitico.”
                Bolletino dell’Atlante Linguistico 8-9: 211.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Fronzaroli1972">Fronzaroli, P. 1972. “Problemi della Lessicografia Comparativa Semitica.” Oriens
                Antiquus 11: 241-262.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Frost1963">Frost, H. 1963. “From Rope to Chain.” Mariner’s Mirror 49: 1.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Frost1969">Frost, H. 1969. “The Stone-Anchors of Ugarit,” in Schaeffer, Ugaritica VI,
                235.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Frost1970">Frost, H. 1970. “Bronze Age Stone Anchors from the Eastern Mediterranean.”
                Mariner’s Mirror 56: 377.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Frost1987">Frost, H. 1987. “How Carthage Lost the Sea.” Natural History 96, No. 12:
                58-67.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gaisford1848">Gaisford, T., ed. 1848. Etymologicum Magnum. Oxford.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Galili1986">Galili, E., et al. 1986. “Bronze Age Ship's Cargo of Copper and Tin.”
                International Journal of Nautical Archaeology and Underwater Exploration 15:
                25-37.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gamble1921">Gamble, T., ed. 1921. Naval Stores: History, Production, Distribution and
                Consumption. Savannah: Review Publishing and Printing Co.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gamillscheg1969">Gamillscheg, E. 1969. Etymologisches Wörterbuch der Französischer Sprache. 2d ed.
                Heidelberg: Carl Winter/Universitätsverlag.</bibl>
            <bibl>García de Palacio, D. 1587. Instrucción Naútica Para Navegar. J.F.Guillén, ed.,
                Madrid, Cultura Hispánica.</bibl>
            <bibl>García Domingo, E. 1983-84. “La Penetración Del Latín En El Griego: Panorámica
                Desde el Siglo III a J.C. Hasta el Siglo Iv d. J.C.” Cuadernos de Filología Clásica
                18: 249-289.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Garcie1483">Garcie, P. F. 1483. Le Grant Routtier et Pyllotage et Encrage de la Mer.
                Poitiers.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Garland1987">Garland, R. 1987. The Piraeus from the Fifth to the First Century B. C.
                Cornell.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Garnsey1983a">Garnsey, P. D. A. 1983. “Grain for Rome,” in P. Garnsey, et al., eds., Trade and Famine in the Ancient World 118-130.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Garnsey1983b">Garnsey, P. D. A., and C. R. Whittaker, eds. 1983. Trade and Famine in the Anicent World. Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Garnsey1983c">Garnsey, P. D. A., et al., eds. 1983. Trade in the Ancient Economy. Los
                Angeles.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Garnsey1985">Garnsey, P. D. A. 1985. “Grain for Athens,” P. Cartledge and F. D. Harvey, eds. Crux: Essays Presented to G. E. M. de Ste. Croix on His 75th Birthday. London:
                Gerald Duckworth &amp; Co.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Garr1000">Garr, W. R. 1985. Dialect Geography of Syria-Palestine 1000-586 B.C.E. University
                of Pennsylvania.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gateau1946">Gateau, A. 1946. “Introduction à l'Étude du Vocabulaire Maritime en Tunisie:
                Technologie du Lûd.” Revue Africaine, nos. 406-409: 140-183.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gateau1966">Gateau, A. 1966. Atlas et Glossaire Nautiques Tunisiens. 2 vols. Beirut: Dar
                el-Machreq.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gaussen1926">Gaussen, H. 1926. Végétation de la Moitié Orientale des Pyrénées. Paris: Paul
                Lechevalier.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gauthier1981">Gauthier, P. 1981. “De Lysias à Aristotle (Ath. Pol. 51.4): Le Commerce du Grain à
                Athènes et les Fonctions des Sitophylaques.” Revue Historique de Droit Français et
                Étranger 59: 5-28.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gelb1957">Gelb, I. J. 1957. Glossary of Old Akkadian. Chicago: University of Chicago
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gelb1968">Gelb, I. J. 1968. “The Word Dragoman in the Ancient Near East.” Glossa 2:
                93-104.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gelb1956">Gelb, I. J., et al., eds. 1956. The Assyrian Dictionary of the Oriental Institute
                of the University of Chicago. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gellius1967">Gellius, Aulus, and C. Hosius, ed. 1967. Noctes Atticae. Stuttgart:
                Teubner.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gerov1980">Gerov, B. 1980. “Die Lateinisch-Griechische Sprachgrenze auf der Balkanhalbinsel,”
                in Die Sprachen im Römischen Reich der Kaiserzeit, 147-66.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gianfrotta1977">Gianfrotta, P. A. 1977. “First Elements for the Dating of the Stone Anchor
                Stocks.” International Journal of Nautical Archaeology 6: 285-292.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gianfrotta1981">Gianfrotta, P. A. and P. Pomey. 1981. Archeologia Subacquea: Storia, Techniche,
                Scoporte Relitte. Milan: Arnoldo Mondadori Editore.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gibson1978">Gibson, J. C. L. 1978. Canaanite Myths and Legends. Edinburgh: Clarke.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Giesecke1983">Giesecke, H. E. 1983. “The Akrotiri Ship Fresco.” International Journal of
                Nautical Archaeology and Underwater Exploration 12, No. 2: 123-143.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gignac1976">Gignac, F. 1976. A Grammar of the Greek Papyri of the Roman And Byzantine Periods,
                Vol. I.: Phonology. Milan.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gili Gaya, S., ed. 1960. Tesoro Lexicógrafo. Madrid.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gillmer1975">Gillmer, T. C. 1975. “The Thera Ship.” Mariner’s Mirror 61:4.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gillmer1978">Gillmer, T. C. 1978. “The Thera Ships: A Reanalysis.” Mariner’s Mirror 64:
                125-134.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gioffré, D. 1962. “Atti Rogati in Chio nella Seconda Metà del XIV Secolo.”
                Bulletino de l’Institut Historique Belge de Rome 34: 319-404.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Glare1982">Glare, P.G.W., ed. 1982 Oxford Latin Dictionary: Oxford Univ. Press</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Glanville1930">Glanville, S. R. K. 1930. “Records of a Royal Dockyard of the Time of Tuthmosis
                III: Papyrus British Museum 10056.” Zeitschrift für Ägyptische Sprache und
                Altertumskunde 66:105-121.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Glanville1932">Glanville, S. R. K. 1932. “Records of a Royal Dockyard of the Time of Tuthmosis
                III: Papyrus British Museum 10056.” Zeitschrift für Ägyptische Sprache und
                Altertumskunde 68:7-41.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Goetz1923">Goetz, G., ed. 1888-1923. Corpus Glossariorum Latinorum. 7 vols.
                Leipzig/Berlin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Goitein1966">Goitein, S. D., ed. 1966. Studies in Islamic History and Institutions.
                Leiden.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Goitein1967">Goitein, S. D. 1967-197. A Mediterranean Society: the Jewish Communities of the
                Arab World as Portrayed in the Documents of the Cairo Geniza. 3 vols.
                Berkeley.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Goitein1968">Goitein, S. D. 1968. “Medieval Tunisia: the Hub of the Mediterranean',” in S. D.
                Goiten, Studies in Islamic History and Institutions.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Gold1981">Gold, E. 1981. Maritime Transport: the Evolution of International Marine Policy
                and Shipping Law. Lexington: Lexington Books, D.C. Heath and Co.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gonzales de Clavijo, R., and I. Sreznevskj 1881. The Spanish Embassy to Samarkand
                1403-1406. St. Petersburg.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Goodman1964">Goodman, W. L. 1964. The History of Woodworking Tools. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Goodwin1987">Goodwin, P. 1987. The Construction and Fitting of the English Man of War
                1650-1850. Annapolis: Naval Institute Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gordiano1956">Gordiano, G. 1956. “The Mediterranean Region,” in Haden Guest et al., eds., A
                World Geography of Forest Resources, 317-353. New York: Ronald Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gordon1965">Gordon, C. H. 1965. Ugaritic Textbook: Grammar, Texts in Transliteration,
                Cuneiform Selections, Glossary, Indices. Rome: Pontificium Institutum
                Biblicum.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gordon1967">Gordon, C. H. 1967. Supplement to the Ugaritic Textbook: Grammar, Texts in
                Transliteration, Cuneiform Selections, Glossary, Indices. Rome: Pontificium
                Institutum Biblicum.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Graeve, M. 1981. “The Ships of the Ancient Near East.” Orientalia Lovaniensia
                Analecta, 7 vol. Louvain: Departement Oriëntalostiek.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Grainger1991">Grainger, J. 1991. Hellenistic Phoenicia. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Grandgent1927">Grandgent, C. H. 1927. From Latin to Italian: An isHtorical Outline of the
                Phonology and Morphology of the Italian Language. Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Granger1962">Granger, F., ed. 1962. Vitruvius on Architecture. 2 vols. Harvard University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gray1974">Gray, D. 1974. Seewesen. Archaeologia Homerica.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Green1988">Green, M. 1988. “In the Aegean: A Ghost Ship Comes to Life.” Smithsonian Magazine
                18, No. 10: 74-88.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Greene1986">Greene, K. 1986. The Archaeology of the Roman Economy. Berkeley: University of
                California Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Greenhill1976">Greenhill, B. 1976. The Archaeology of the Boat: a New Introductory Study.
                London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Greenhill1988">Greenhill, B. and S. Manning. 1988. Evolution of the Wooden Ship. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gugliemi1974">Gugliemi, M. 1974. “Sulla Navigazione in eta Micenea.” Parola del Passato 26:
                418-435.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Guglielmotti1889">Guglielmotti, A. 1889. Vocabolario Marino e Militare. Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Gugliemotti1893">Gugliemotti, P. A. 1886-1893. Storia della Marina Pontificale nel Medio Evo. 10
                vols. Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Guillou1970">Guillou, A. 1970. Culture et Société en Italie Byzantine (VIe- XIe Siècles).
                London: Collected Studies Series, Variorum Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Guilmartin1974">Guilmartin, J. F. 1974. Gunpowder and Galleys: Changing Technology and
                Mediterranean Warfare at Sea in the Sixteenth Century. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Guilmartin1981">Guilmartin, J. F. 1981. “The Tactics of the Battle of Lepanto Clarified: the
                Impact of Social, Economic, and Political Factors on Sixteenth Century Galley
                Warefare,” in Symonds, C. L. ed., New Aspects of Naval History: Selected Papers
                Presented at the Fourth Naval History Symposium, 41-65. Annapolis: Naval Institute
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hadjidaki1988">Hadjidaki, E. 1988. “Preliminary Report of Investigations at the Harbor of
                Phalasma in West Crete.” American Journal of Archaeology 92: 463-479.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hägg, R. and N. Marinatos, eds. 1984. The Minoan Thalassocracy: Myth and Reality.
                Gӧteborg: Paul Astrӧms Fӧrlag.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hägglund, E. 1951. Chemistry of Wood. New York: Academic Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Haldane1990a">Haldane, C. W. 1990. “Shipwrecked Plant Remains.” Near Eastern Archaeology
                (formerly Biblical Archaeologist) 53, No. 1: 55-60.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Haldane1990b">Haldane, D. 1990. “Anchors of Antiquity.” Near Eastern Archaeology (formerly Biblical Archaeologist) 53, No. 1: 19-24.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hankey1981">Hankey, V. 1981. “The Aegean Interest in El Amarna.” Journal of Mediterranean Anthropology and Archaeology I: 38-49.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Harden1962">Harden, D. 1962. The Phoenicians. New York: Praeger.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Harding1984">Harding, A. F. 1984. The Mycenaeans and Europe. New York: Academic Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Harland1984">Harland, J. 1984. Seamanship in the Age of Sail. Annapolis: Naval Institute
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Harley1987">Harley, J. B. and D. Woodward, eds. 1987. The History of Cartography: Volume One:
                Cartography in Prehistoric, Ancient, and Medieval Europe and the Mediterranean.
                Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Harper1928">Harper, G. M., Jr. 1928. “Commercial Relations Between Egypt and Syria.” American
                Journal of Philology XLIX: 1.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Harris1988">Harris, M. and N. Vincent, eds. 1988. The Romance Languages. New York: Oxford
                University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Harris1989">Harris, W. V. 1989. Ancient Literacy. Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Harris1936">Harris, Z. S. 1936. Grammar of the Phoencian Language. New Haven.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Harris1939">Harris, Z. S. 1939. Development of the Canaanitic Dialects. American Oriental
                Association.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hawkins1977">Hawkins, J.D., ed. 1977. Trade in the Ancient Near East: Papers Presented to the
                XXIII Rencontre Assyriologique Internationale University of Birmingham 5-9 July,
                1976. London: British School of Archaeology in Iraq.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Haywood1991">Haywood, J. 1991. Dark Age Naval Power: A Reassessment of Frankish and Anglo-Saxon
                Seafaring. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Heers1961">Heers, J. 1961. Economie et Société à Gênes XIVe au XVe Siècle. London: Variorum
                Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Heltzer1977">Heltzer, M. 1977. “The Metal Trade of Ugarit and the Problem of Transportation of
                Commercial Goods.” Iraq 39: 203-211.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hemmerdinger1969">Hemmerdinger, B. 1969. “Noms Communs Grecs d’Origine Égyptienne.” Glotta 46:
                238-247.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hengel1980">Hengel, M. 1980. Jews, Greeks and Barbarians: Aspects of the Hellenization of
                Judaism in the Pre-Christian Period. Philadelphia: Fortress Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Herlihy1969">Herlihy, D., ed. 1969. Economy, Society and Government in Medieval Italy, Essays
                in Honor of Robert L. Reynolds. Kent: Kent State University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hermansen1982">Hermansen, G. 1982. “The Stuppatores and Their Guild in Ostia.” American Journal
                of Archaeology 86: 120-126.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hesseling1903">Hesseling, D. C. 1903. Les Mots Maritimes Empruntés Par le Grec Aux Langues
                Romanes. Verhandelingen der Koninklijke Akademie van Wetenschappen te
                Amsterdam.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Heyd1886">Heyd, W. 1885-1886. Histoire du Commerce du Levant au Moyen Âge. Leipzig.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hirschfeld1990">Hirschfeld, N. 1990. “The Ship of Saint Paul, Part I: Historical Background.” Near
                Eastern Archaeology (formerly Biblical Archaeologist) 53, No. 1: 25-30.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hoare1967">Hoare, A. 1967. A Short Italian Dictionary. Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hocker1987">Hocker, F. M. 1987. “Sheets (Poziae) in the Medieval Lateen Rig.” Mariner’s Mirror
                73: 367-368</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hocquet1979">Hocquet, J. -C. 1978-1979. Le Sel et la Fortune de Venise. 2 vols. Sarbonne:
                Presses Universitaires de Lille.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hocquet1981">Hocquet, J. -C. 1981. “Gens de Mer à Venise: Diversité des Statuts, Conditions de
                Vie et de Travail sur les Navires,” in Le Genti del Mare Mediterraneo, edited by R.
                Ragosta, 103-168.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hoffner1973">Hoffner, H. A., ed. 1973. “Orient and Occident: Essays Presented to Cyrus H.
                Gordon on His SIxty-Fifth Birthday.” Alter Orient und Altes Testament 22.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hohlfelder1987">Hohlfelder, R. L. 1987. “Herod the Great's City on the Sea: Caesarea Maritima.”
                National Geographic Research 171, No. 2: 261-279.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Holloway3000">Holloway, R. R. 1981. Italy and the Aegean, 3000-700 B. C. Louvain.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Holmes1975">Holmes, Y. L. 1975. “The Foreign Trade of Cyprus During the Late Bronze Age,” in
                Robertson, N., ed., The Archaeology of Cyprus: Recent Developments.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Holum1988">Holum, Kenneth G., Hohlfelder, Robert L, Bull, Robert J., &amp; Raban, Avner 1988
                King Herod's dream: Cæsarea on the sea: New York/London, W.W. Norton (AH)</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hooker1976">Hooker, J. T. 1976. Mycenaean Greece. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hopf1873">Hopf, C., trans. 1873. Cronaca di Morea: Chroniques Gréce-Romanes. Berlin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hopper1979">Hopper, R. J. 1979. Trade and Industry in Classical Greece. London: Thames &amp;
                Hudson.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hornell1941">Hornell, J. 1941. “Sea-trade in Ancient Times.” Antiquity 15, 233.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hort1916">Hort, A., ed. 1916. Theophrastus: Enquiry into Plants. 2 vols. Loeb.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hosius1967">Hosius, C., ed. 1967. Noctes Atticae (Aulus Gellius). Stuttgart: Teubner.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Houaiss1967">Houaiss, A., and C. P. Avery, eds. 1967. The New Appleton Dictionary of the
                English and Portuguese Languages. New York: Appleton-Century-Crofts.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hourani1951">Hourani, G. F. 1951. Arab Seafaring in the Indian Ocean in Ancient and Early
                Medieval Times. Princeton University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Howarth1977">Howarth, D. A. 1977. Dhows. New York: Quartet Books.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Howse1973">Howse, D., and M. Sanderson. 1973. The Sea Chart. New York: McGraw-Hill.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hrochova1967">Hrochova, V. 1967. “Le Commerce Vénitien et les Changements dans l'Importance des
                Centres de Commerce en Grèce du 13e au 15e Siècle.” Studi Veneziani 9: 3-34.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hunt1934">Hunt, A.S., and C. C. Edgar. 1932-1934. Select Papyri. 3 vols. Loeb.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hussey1966">Hussey, J. M., ed. 1966. The Cambridge Medieval History Volume IV: The Byzantine
                Empire: Part I: Byzantium and Its Neighbors. Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Immerwahr1960">Immerwahr, S. A. 1960. “Mycenaean Trade and Colonization.” Archaeology 13:
                4-13.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Isager1975">Isager, S., and M. H. Hansen. 1975. Aspects of Athenian Society in the Fourth
                Century B.C.: A Historical Introduction to and Commentary on the Paragraphe-speeches
                and the Speech Against Dionysodorus in the Corpus Demosthenicum (XXXII-XXXVIII and
                LVI). J.H. Rosenmeier, trans. Odense: Odense University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jacoby1979">Jacoby, D. 1979. Recherches sur la Méditerranée Orientale du XIIe au XVe Siècle:
                Peuples, Sociétés, Economies. London: Variorum Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jados1973">Jados, S. S. 1973. The Consulate of the Sea and Related Documents. Tuscaloosa:
                University of Alabama Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jal1840">Jal, A. 1840. Archéologie Navale: Tome I &amp; II. Paris: Arthus Bertrand.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jal1848">Jal, A. 1848. Glossaire Nautique: Répertoire Polyglotte de Termes de Marine
                Anciens et Modernes. Paris: Firmin Didot.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jal1970">Jal, A. 1970. Nouveau Glossaire Nautique. Paris: Editions du Centre National de la
                Recherche Scientifique.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="James1000">James, E. 1982. The Origins of France: From Clovis to the Capetian, 500-1000.
                London: The Macmillan Press Ltd.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jamison1957">Jamison, E. 1957. Âdmiral Eugenius of Sicily. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jane1988">Jane, C. ed. 1988. The Four Voyages of Columbus. New York: Dover
                Publications</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jasny1944">Jasny, M. 1944. The Wheats of Classical Antiquity. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jehel1985">Jehel, G. 1985. Aigues-Mortes, un Port Pour un Roi: Les Capétiens et la
                Méditerranée. Roanne: Horvath.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jenkins1980">Jenkins, N. 1980. The Boat Beneath the Pyramid: King Cheops’ Royal Ship. Austin:
                Holt, Rinehart and Winston.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jirecek1903">Jirecek, C. 1901-1903. Die Romanen in den Städten Dalmatiens Während des
                Mittelalters. 3 vols. Vienna: Denkenschriften der Kaiserlichen Akademie der
                Wissenschaften in Wien.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Johnstone1980">Johnstone, P. 1980. The Sea-Craft of Prehistory. London: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Johnston1985">Johnston, P. 1985. Ship and Boat Models in Ancient Greece. Annapolis: Naval
                Institute Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Joinville, J. 1963. “Histoire de Saint Louis.” In Historiens et Chroniqueurs du
                Moyen Âge, 19. A. Pauphilet and E. Pognon, eds. Paris: Bibliothèque de la
                Pléiade.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jones1964">Jones, A. H. M. 1964. The Later Roman Empire, 284-602: A Social, Economic, and
                Administrative Survey. 3 vols. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Jones1961">Jones, T. B., and J. W. Snyder. 1961. Sumerian Economic Texts from the Third Ur
                Dynasty. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Judge1978">Judge, J. 1978. “Minoans and Mycenaeans: Sea Kings of the Aegean.” National
                Geographic Research 153.2: 142-85.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kahane1938">Kahane, R. 1938. “Italienische Marinewörter im Neugriechiscen Anlässlich D.C.
                Hesseling, Les Mots…” Journal of Roman Archaeology 22: 510-582.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kahane1939">Kahane, H. 1939. “Zur Neugriechischen Seemanssprache Anlässlich Vidos, Parole Marinaresche.” Byzantinisch-Neugriechiscen Jahrbücher 15: 91-129.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kahane1940a">Kahane, H. 1939-1940. “Italo-Byzantinische Etymologien: Scala.”
                Byzantinisch-Neugriechischen Jahrbücher 16: 33-58.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kahane1940b">Kahane, H., and R. Kahane. 1940. “Italienische Ortsnamen in Griechenland.” Texte und Forschungen zur Byzantinisch-Neugriechiscen Philologie 36: 1-379. Athens.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Kahane1954">Kahane, H., et al. 1953-1954. “Venetian Nautical Terms in Dalmatia.” Romance
                Philology 7: 156-170, 333-342.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kahane1958">Kahane, H., et al. 1958. The Lingua Franca in the Levant: Turkish Nautical Terms of Italian and Greek Origin. Urbana: University of Illinois Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kahane1967">Kahane, H., et al., and Cortelazzo, M., trans. 1967. Glossario Degli Antichi
                Portolani Italiani. Florence.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kang1973">Kang, S. T. 1973. Sumerian Economic Texts from the Umma Archive. Urbana:
                University of Illinois Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Kapitän, G. 1984. “Ancient Anchors: Technology and Classification.” International
                Journal of Nautical Archaeology 13: 33-44.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Karjanto1980">Karjanto, I. 1980. “Minderheiten und Ihre Sprachen in der Haupstadt Rom,” in
                Neumann, G., and J. Untermann, eds. 1980. Die Sprachen im Römischen Reich der
                Kaiserzeit, 83-102.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kemp1976">Kemp, P. 1976. The Oxford Companion to Ships and the Sea. Oxford University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kenyon1899">Kenyon, F. G. 1899. The Paleography of Greek Papyri. Oxford University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Kerchove, R. 1961. International Maritime Dictionary. 2 vols. New York: Van
                Nostrand Reinhold.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kienast1966">Kienast, D. 1966. Untersuchungen zu dem Kriegsflotten der Römischen Kaiserzeit.
                Rudolf Habelt Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kilburn1959">Kilburn, K., ed., trans. 1959. Lucian. 8 vols., Cambridge: Loeb Library, Harvard
                University.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kindermann1934">Kindermann, H. 1934. “‘Schiff’ im Arabischen, Untersuchung über Vorkommen und
                Bedeutung der Termini.” diss., Zwickau i. S.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kindermann1936">Kindermann, H. 1916-1936. “Al-Safīna.” Encyclopedia of Islam, Supplement: 192-195.
                Brill.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kirk1949">Kirk, G. S. 1949. “Ships on Geometric Vases.” Annual of the British School at
                Athens 44:93-153.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kirsch1990">Kirsch, P. 1990. Galleon: the Great Ships of the Armada Era: Annapolis, Naval
                Institute Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Klengel1979">Klengel, H. 1979. Handel under Händler in Alten Orient. Vienna: Hermann Böhlaus
                Nachfolger.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kohler1243">Kohler, C., ed. 1913. Phillipe de Novare, Memoires, 1218-1243 [Gestes des
                Chiprois]. Paris: Champion.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kohler1967">Kohler, L., and W. Baumgarther. 1967. Hebräisches und Aramäisches Lexikon zum
                Alten Testament. 3rd ed. Leiden.</bibl>
            <bibl>Köster, A. 1923. Das Antike Seewesen. Berlin.</bibl>
            <bibl>Köster, A. 1924. Shiffahrt under Handelsverkehr des Östlichen Mittelmeeres im 3.
                u. 2. Jahrtausend v. Chr. Hinrichs.</bibl>
            <bibl>Köster, A. 1934. Studien zur Geschichte des Antiken Seewesens. Leipzig: Klio
                Beiheft.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kourbelis1950">Kourbelis, N. 1950. Αγγλοελληνικόν Λεξικόν Ναυτιλιακών Όρων [Anglo-Hellenic
                Lexicon of Nautical Terms]. Athens.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Krahe1952">Krahe, H. 1952. “Griech ‘λέμβος’, Lat. ‘lembus’- Eine Illyrische
                Schiffsbezeichnung?” Gymnasium 59: 79.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Krantz1982">Krantz, E. S. 1982. Des Schiffes Weg Mitten im Meer: Beiträge zur Erforschung der
                Nautischen Terminologies des Alten Testaments. Lund: Coniectanea Biblica,
                Gleerup.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Krauss1898">Krauss, S. 1898. Griechische und lateinische Lehnwörter im Talmud, Midrasch und
                Targum. 2 vol.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Krauss1910">Krauss, S. 1910-12. Talmudische Archäologie. 3 vols.</bibl>
            <bibl>Krekić, B. 1976. “Contributions of Foreigners to Dubrovnik’s Economic Growth in
                the Late Middle Ages.” Viator 9: 375-394.</bibl>
            <bibl>Krekić, B. 1980. Dubrovnik, Italy, and the Balkans in the Later Middle Ages.
                London, Variorum Reprints, Collected Studies Series 125.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kretschmer1909">Kretschmer, K. 1909. Die Italienische Portolane des Mittelalters: Ein Beitrag zur
                Geschicte der Kartographie und Nautik. Berlin: E. S. Mittler und Sohn.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kreutz1976">Kreutz, B. M. 1976. “Ships, Shipping and the Implications of Change in the Early
                Medieval Mediterranean.” Viator 7: 79-110.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kreutz1991">Kreutz, B. M. 1991. Before the Normans--Southern Italy in the Ninth and Tenth
                Centuries. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Krueger1985">Krueger, H. C. 1985. Navi e Proprietà Navale a Genova Seconda Meta del Sec. XII.
                Atti Della Società Ligure Di Storia Patria.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Kurt1979">Kurt, C. 1979. Seemäinishe Fachausdrücke bei Homer, unter Berücksichtigung Hesiods
                und der Lyriker bs Bachylides. Göttingen: Vanenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Labat1962">Labat, R. 1962. “Le Rayonnement de la Langue et de l'Écriture Akkadienne au
                Deuxième Millénaire Avant Notre Ère” Syria 39: 1-29.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Laiou1982">Laiou, A. E. 1982. “Quelques Observations sur l'Économie et la Société de Crète
                Vénitienne (ca. 1270-1305),” in Bisancio e l'Italia, Raccolta di Studi in Memoria di
                Agostino Pertusi. Milan.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Laiou1984">Laiou, A. E. 1984. “Observations on the Results of the Fourth Crusade: Greeks and
                Latins in Port and Market.” Medievalia et Humanistica, New Series, No. 12: 33-45,
                Rowman &amp; Allenheld.</bibl>
            <bibl>Laiou-Thomadakis, A. E. 1980. “The Byzantine Economy in the Mediterranean Trade
                System, Thirteenth-Fifteenth Centuries.” Dumbarton Oaks Papers 34: 177-222.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Lane1933">Lane, F. C. 1933. “Venetian Shipping During the Commercial Revolution.” American
                Historical Review 38: 219-239.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1550">Lane, F. C. 1934. “Naval Architecture, About 1550.” Mariner’s Mirror 20:
                24-49.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1449">Lane, F. C. 1944. Andrea Barbarigo, Merchant of Venice, 1418-1449. Baltimore:
                Johns Hopkins University Press.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Lane1994">Lane, F. C. 1994. Venetian Ships and Shipbuilders of the Renaissance. Baltimore:
                Johns Hopkins University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1957">Lane, F. C. 1957. “Fleets and Fairs,” in Studi in Onore di Armando Sapori, vol. 1,
                651-663. Milan.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1962a">Lane, F. C. 1962. “Cargaisons de Coton et Réglementations Médiévales Contre la
                Surcharge des Navires -Venise.” Revue d'Histoire Économique et Sociale 40:
                21-31.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1962b">Lane, F. C. 1962. “La Marine Marchande et le Trafic Maritime de Venise À Travers
                les Siècles.” in Mollat, Michel, ed., Les Sources de l'Histoire Maritime en Europe
                du Moyen Âge au XVIII Siècle, p. 7-32. Paris: Actes du Quatrième Colloque
                International d'Histoire Maritime, SEVPEN.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1350">Lane, F. C. 1962. “Maritime Law and Administration 1250-1350,” in Studi in Onore
                di Amintore Fanfani, vol. 3, p. 21-50.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1300">Lane, F. C. 1963. “Merchant Galleys, 1300-34: Private and Communal Operation.”
                Speculum 38: 179-205.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1964">Lane, F. C. 1964. “Tonnages, Medieval and Modern.” Economic History Review, 2d.
                Series, 17: 213-233.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1966">Lane, F. C. 1966. Venice and history. The Collected Papers of Frederick C. Lane.
                Baltimore, Johns Hopkins University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1968">Lane, F. C. 1968. “Pepper Prices Before da Gama.” Journal of Economic History 28:
                590-597.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lane1973">Lane, F. C. 1973. Venice--a Maritime Republic. Baltimore, Johns Hopkins University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Larsen1967">Larsen, M. T. 1967. Old Assyrian Caravan Procedures. Istanbul: Nederlands
                Historich-Archaeologish Institut in Het Nabije Oosten.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Laures1987">Laures, F. F. 1987. “The Warships of the Kings of Aragon and Their Fighting
                Tactics During the 13th and 14th Centuries AD.” International Journal of Nautical
                Archaeology and Underwater Exploration 16: 19-29.</bibl>
            <bibl>Leighton A. C. 1972 Transport and Communication in Early Medieval Europe, AD
                500-1100. United Kingdom: Newton Abbott.</bibl>
            <bibl>Leitão, H. 1963. Dicionario da Linguagem de Marinha Antiga e Actual. Lisbon:
                Centro de Estudos Historicos Ultramarinos.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lesko1982">Lesko, L. H. 1982. Dictionary of Late Egyptian. 4 vols. B. C. Scrike.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lesky1947">Lesky, A. 1947. Thalatta: Der Weg der Griechen zum Meer. Vienna: Ayer
                Company.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lever1963">Lever, D.1819 (1963). The Young Sea Officer's Sheet Anchor--Or A Key to the
                Leading of Rigging and to Practical Seamanship. 2d ed. London, New York: Edward W.
                Sweetman Company.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lewis1100">Lewis, A. R. 1951. Naval Power and Trade in the Mediterranean AD 500-1100 .
                Princeton.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lewis1978">Lewis, A. R. 1978. The Sea and Medieval Civilizations. London: Variorum.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lewis1980">Lewis, A. R. 1980. “The Catalan Failure in Acculturation in Frankish Greece and
                the Islamic World During the Fourteenth Century.” Viator 11: 361-370.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lewis1986">Lewis, A. R., and T. J. Runyan. 1986 European Naval and Maritime History,
                300-1500: Indiana University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lewis1884">Lewis, C. T., and C. Short. 1884. A New Latin Dictionary. New York: Harper &amp;
                Brothers.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Liddell1968">Liddell, H., et al. 1968. A Greek-English Lexicon : Oxford University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lieberman1942">Lieberman, S. 1942. Greek in Jewish Palestine. New York: The Jewish Theological
                Seminary of America.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Linder1970">Linder, E. 1970. “The Maritime Texts of Ugarit: A Study in Late Bronze Shipping.”
                Dissertation. Brandeis University.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Linder1973">Linder, E. 1973. “Naval Warfare in the El-Amarna Age,” in Blackman, D. J, ed.
                Marine Archaeology. London: Colston Papers.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lipinski1979">Lipinski, E. 1979. “An Ugaritic Letter to Amenophis III Concerning Trade with
                Alašiya.” Iraq 39: 213-217.</bibl>
            <bibl>Löfstedt, E. 1959. Late Latin. Oslo: Aschehoug.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lombard1958">Lombard, M. 1958. “Arsenaux et Bois de Marine dans la Méditerranée Musulmane
                (VIIe-XIe Siècles,” in Mollat, ed., Le Navire et l'Économie Maritime, 53-106.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lombard1979">Lombard, M. 1979. “La Marina Adriatica nel Quadro dell’Alto Medioevo (VII-XVI
                Secolo)", in Sotrie de la Civiltà Veneziana, vol. 1, 107-114. Florence.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Longnon1911">Longnon, J., trans. 1911. Libre de la Conqueste de la Princée de l’Morée.
                Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lopez1938">Lopez, R. S. 1938. Storia delle Colonie Genovesi nel Mediterraneo. Bologna.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Lopez1954">Lopez, R. S. 1954. “Les Influences Orientales et l'Éveil Économique de
                l’Occident.” Cahiers d’Histoire Mondiale 1:594-622. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lopez1955a">Lopez, R. S. 1955. “Venezia e le Grandi Linee dell'Expansione Commerciale nel Secolo XIII,” in La Civiltà Veneziana del Secolo di Marco Polo, 37-82. Florence:
                Sansoni.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lopez1959">Lopez, R. S. 1959. “The Role of Trade in the Economic Readjustment of Byzantium in  the Seventh Century.” Dumbarton Oaks Papers 8:69-85.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lopez1965">Lopez, R. S. 1965. “L’Importanza del Mondo Islamico nella Vita Economica Europea.” Settimane di Studio del Centro Italiano di Studi sull’Alto Medioevo 12:
                433-460.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lopez1967">Lopez, R. S. 1967. The Birth of Europe. New York: M. Evans &amp; Company.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lopez1974">Lopez, R. S. 1974. “Foreigners in Byzantium.” Bulletin de l’Institut Historique Belge de Rome 44: 341-352.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lopez1975">Lopez, R. S. 1975. Su e Giù per la Storia de Genova. Genoa.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lopez1350">Lopez, R. S. 1976. The Commercial Revolution of the Middle Ages, 950-1350.
                Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lopez1978">Lopez, R. S. 1978. Byzantium and the World Around It: Economic and Institutional Relations. London: Variorum Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lopez1955b">Lopez, R. S., and I. W. Raymond. 1955. Medieval Trade in the Mediterranean World. New York: Columbia Univeristy Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lorenzo1864">Lorenzo, J. de, et al. 1864. Diccionario Marítimo Español, que Además de las Voces de Navegación Y Maniobra en los Buques de Vela, Contiene las Equivalencias en
                Francés, Inglés e Italiano, y las Más Usadas en los Buques de Vapor, Formado con
                Presencia de los Mejores Datos Publicados Hasta el Día. Madrid: T. Fortanet.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Lucic1973">Lucic, J. 1971-1973. “Gli Stranieri a Ragusa nel Medioevo.” Bolletino
                dell’Atlante Linguistico Mediterraneo 13-15: 345-348.</bibl>
            <bibl>Lüddeckens, E.1980. “Ägypten,” in Neumann, G., and J. Untermann, eds. 1980. Die
                Sprachen im Römischen Reich der Kaiserzeit, 241-266. Cologne: Bonn.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lurier1969">Lurier, H. E., trans. 1969. Chronicle of Morea. New York.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Lutrell1981">Lutrell, A. 1981. “Late Medieval Galley Oarsmen,” in Le Genti del Mare
                Mediterraneo, 87-101.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Luzzatto1961a">Luzzatto, G. 1961. An Economic History of Italy from the Fall of the Roman Empire to the Beginning of the Sixteenth Century. trans. by P. Jones. London: Routledge
                &amp; Kegan Paul.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Luzzatto1961b">Luzzatto, G. 1961. Storia economica di Venezia. Venice.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Macchi1970">Macchi, V. 1970. Sansoni-Harrap Standard Italian-English, English-Italian
                Dictionary.” edited by Harrap, G. G. University of California.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Machado1967">Machado, J. P. 1967. Dicionário Etimológico da Língua Portuguesa. 2d ed., Lisbon: Confluência.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Macleod1987">Macleod, M. D., ed. 1987. Luciani Opera. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Malamat1973">Malamat, A. 1973. “The Aramaeans,” in D.J. Wiseman, ed., Peoples of Old Testament Times, 134-155.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mallett1967">Mallett, M. E. 1967. The Florentine Galleys in the Fifteenth Century with the Diary of Luca di Maso degli Albizzi Captain of the Galleys 1429-1430. Oxford: The
                Clarendon Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Manessy-Guitton, J. 1979. “Ikria et la Base *ik-.” Annales de la Faculté des
                Lettres et Sciences Humaines de Nice 35:39-57.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Manfroni1902">Manfroni, C. 1897-1902. Storia de la Marina Italiana. 3 vols. Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Manwayring1972">Manwayring, H. 1644 (1972). Seaman's Dictionary. Menston, England: The Scholar Press Ltd.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Marcille1941a">Marcille, R. 1941. “La Pax Antique.” Revue Tunisienne 216-219.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Marcille1941b">Marcille, R. 1941. “La Résine et la Poix dans Pline.” Revue Tunisienne
                220-223.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Marcus1978">Marcus, D. 1978. Manual of Akkadian. University Press of America.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Marcus1981">Marcus, D. 1981. Manual of Babylonian Jewish Aramaic. University Press of
                America.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Martines1582">Martines, J. 1582 (1915). Portolan Atlas Joan Martines en Messina Año 1582. New
                York: Hispanic Society of America.</bibl>
            <bibl>Martinez-Hidalgo, J. M. 1966. Columbus' Ships. Massachusetts: Barre
                Publishers.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Martorell1980">Martorell, J. and M. J. de Galba.1460-1490 (1926/1980). Tirant lo Blanc. 5 vols.
                Barcelona: Els Nostres Classics.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Masson1896">Masson, P. 1896. Histoire du Commerce Français dans le Levant au XVIII Siècle.
                Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Masson1911">Masson, P. 1911. Histoire du Commerce Français dans le Levant au XVII Siècle.
                Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Masson1781">Masson, P. 1938. “Les Galères de France, 1481-1781.” Annales de la Faculté des
                Lettres d'Aix 20: fasc. 1-2. Aix-en-Provence.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Masson1966">Masson, E. 1966. Recherches sur les Plus Ancien Emprunts Sémitiques en Grec.
                Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mastropasqua1967">Mastropasqua, V. 1967. Technical Nautical Dictionary: English-Italian,
                Italian-English. Genoa: M. Bozzi.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Mata Carriazo, J., ed. G. Diez de Games. (1940). El Victorial, Crónica de Don
                Pero Niño. Madrid: Colección de Crónicas Españolas I.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Matthews1974">Matthews, S. W. 1974. The Phoenicians- Sea Lords of Antiquity. National
                Geographic.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Matthiae1981">Matthiae, P. 1981. Ebla: an Empire Rediscovered. Garden City, New York:
                Doubleday.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Matz1987">Matz, F. and H-G. Buchholz,eds. 1967-1987. Archaeologia Homerica.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="May1973">May, W. E. 1973. A History of Marine Navigation. Henley-on-Thames: G.T. Foulis
                &amp; Company, Ltd.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="McCaslin1980">McCaslin, D. E. 1980. “Stone Anchors in Antiquity: Coastal Settlements and
                Maritime Trade-Routes in the Eastern Mediterranean Circa 1600-1050 B.C.” Studies in
                Mediterranean Archaeology 61. Goteborg: Paul Astroms Forlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="McGowan1981">McGowan, A. 1981. The Ship: Tiller and Whipstaff--the Development of the Sailing
                Ship 1400-1700. London: National Maritime Museum.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="McGready1969">McGready, A. G. 1969. “Egyptian Words in the Greek Vocabulary.” Glotta
                46:247-254.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="McNeill1797">McNeill, W. H. 1973. Venice--the Hinge of Europe 1081-1797. University of Chicago
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Medina, P. 1545. Arte de Navegar.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mee1978">Mee, C. 1978. “Aegean Trade and Settlement in Anatolia in the Second Millennium B.
                C.” Anatolian Studies 28:121-156.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Meiggs1973">Meiggs, R.. 1973. Roman Ostia. 2d. ed. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Meiggs1983">Meiggs, R.. 1983. Trees and Timber in the Ancient Mediterranean World. Oxford
                University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Meijer1986">Meijer, F. J. 1986. A History of Seafaring in the Classical World. New York: St.
                Martin's.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Meisel1977">Meisel, J. M. 1977. Langues en Contact. Tübingen: TBL Verlag Gunter Narr.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mellink1986">Mellink, M. J., ed. 1986. Troy and the Trojan War. Bryn Mawr College.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mercer1939">Mercer, S. A. B. 1939. The Tell El-Amarna Tablets. Toronto.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Merrien1969">Merrien, J. 1969. La Vie Quotidienne des Marins au Moyen Âge (des Wikings aux
                Galères). Librairie Hachette.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Merrillees1972">Merrillees, R. S. 1972. “Aegean Bronze Age Relations with Egypt.” American Journal
                of Archaeology 76: 281-294.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Merzagora1929">Merzagora, M. 1929. “La Navigazione in Egitto nell'Età Greco-Romana.” Aegyptus 10:
                105-148.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Meyer1895">Meyer, G. 1895. “Neugriechische Studien III: Die Lateinischen Lehnworte im
                Neugriechischen.” Sitzungsberichte der K. Akademie der Wissenschaften,
                Philosophisch-historische Classe 132. Vienna.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Mézières, P. 1969. Le Songe du Vieil Pelerin. 2 vols., edited by G.W Coopland.
                Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Miège, J. 1990. Navigation et Migrations en Méditerranée: De la Préhistoire à Nos
                Jours. CNRS Éditions.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Miglorini1974">Miglorini, B., and A. Duro, eds. 1974. Prontuario Etimologico della Lingua
                Italiana. S.F. Vanni.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Miglorini1984">Miglorini, B., and T. G. Griffith. 1984. The Italian Language. 2d. ed. London:
                Faber &amp; Faber.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Migne1866">Migne, J. P., ed. 1857-1866. Patrologiae Graecae. Paris: J. P. Migne Imprimerie
                Catholique.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mihăescu, H. 1978. La Langue Latine dans le Sud-est de l'Europe. Bucharest.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Milani1973">Milani, V. I. 1973. The Written Language of Christopher Columbus. New York: State
                University of New York.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Millar1983">Millar, F. G. B. 1983. “The Phoenician Cities: a Case Study of Hellenisation.”
                Proceedings of the Cambridge Philological Society 29:55-71.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Miskimin1460">Miskimin, H. A. 1969. The Economy of Early Renaissance Europe, 1300-1460.
                Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Miskimin1600">Miskimin, H. A. 1969. The Economy of Later Renaissance Europe, 1460-1600.
                Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mistral1886">Mistral, F. 1878-1886. Lou Tresor dóu Felibrige, ou Dictionnaire
                Provençal-Français. 2 vols. Aix-en-Provence: Veuve Remondet-Aubin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mohler1948">Mohler, S. 1948. “Sails and Oars in the Aeneid.” Transactions of the American
                Philological Association 79: 46-62.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mollat1958">Mollat, M. 1958. Le Navire et l'Économie Maritime du Moyen Âge au XVIIIe Siècle
                Principalement en Méditerranée. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mommsen1895">Mommsen, T., et al., eds. 1872-1895. Corpus Iuris Civilis. Berlin: Apud
                Weidmannos.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Moore1912">Moore, A., ed. 1912. “The Sea Scene from the Complaynt of Scotlande,” in The
                Naval Miscellany 2 (Publications of the Navy Records Society 40: 67-84).
                London.</bibl>
            <bibl>Morales Belda, F. 1970. La Marina de Al-Andalus. Barcelona.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Moran1987">Moran, W., et al. 1987. Les Lettres d’El-Amarna. Paris: Éditions du Cerf.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Moravcsik1967">Moravcsik, G., ed., and R.J.H. Jenkins, translat. 1967. De Administrando Imperio
                [of Constantine VII Porphyrogenitus]. Washington D.C.: Dumbarton Oaks Center for
                Byzantine Studies.</bibl>
            <bibl>Morel-Fatio, A., trans. 1885. Libro de los Fechos et Conquistas del Principado de
                la Morea. Geneva.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Moretti1972">Moretti, L. 1968-1972. Inscriptiones Graecae Urbis Romae. 2 vols. Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Morison1942">Morison, S. E. 1942. Admiral of the Ocean Sea. Boston: Little, Brown &amp;
                Co.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Morrison1947">Morrison, J. 1947. “Notes on Certain Greek Nautical Terms and on Three Passages in
                IGII2 1632.” Classical Quarterly 41:122-135.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Morrison1968">Morrison, J. S., and R. T. Williams. 1968. Greek Oared Ships, 900-322 B.C.
                Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Moscati1959">Moscati, S. 1959. “Snella Storia del Noma Canaan.” Studia Biblica et Orientalia
                3:266-269. Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Moscati1968">Moscati, S. 1968. The World of the Phonecians. New York: Frederick A.
                Praeger.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Moscati2001">Moscati, S., ed. 2001. The Phonecians. Abbeville Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mossé, C. 1983. “The World of the Emporium in the Private Speeches of
                Demosthenes,” in Garnsey, et al., eds. Trade in the Ancient Economy.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mott1990">Mott, L. V. 1990. “Ships of the 13th-Century Catalan Navy.” International Journal
                of Nautical Archaeology 19: 101-112.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mott1600">Mott, L. V. 1991. The Development of the Rudder, A.D. 100-1600: a Technological
                Tale. M.A. thesis. Texas A&amp;M University.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Motzo1947">Motzo, B. R., ed. 1947. Il Compasso da Navigare- Opera Italiana della Metà del
                Secolo XIII : Annali della Facoltà di Lettere e Filosofia della Università di
                Cagliari 8.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Muhly1970">Muhly, J. D. 1970. “Homer and the Phoneicians.” Berytus 19:19-64.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Muhly1973">Muhly, J. D. 1973. Copper and Tin: The Distribution of Mineral Resources and the
                Nature of the Metals Trade in the Bronze Age. New Haven.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Muhly1985">Muhly, J. D. 1985. “Sources of TIme and the Beginnings of Bronze Metallurgy.”
                American Journal of Archaeology 89:275-291.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Muller1855">Muller, C. 1855. Geographi Graeci Minores. vol. I. Paris: Collection Didot.,
                ,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Murphy1977">Murphy, J. P., ed. 1977. Ora Maritima. Chicago: Ares.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Mussies1976">Mussies, G. 1976. “Greek in Palestine and the Diaspora,” Safrai, S., and M. Stern,
                eds., The Jewish People in the First Century,1040-1064. Philadelphia: Fortress
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Nadvi1941">Nadvi, S. S. 1941. “Arab Navigation.” Islamic Culture (Hyderabad) 15(4):
                435-449.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Nadvi1942a">Nadvi, S. S. 1942. “Arab Navigation.” Islamic Culture (Hyderabad) 16 (1):
                72-87.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Nadvi1942b">Nadvi, S. S. 1942. “Arab Navigation.” Islamic Culture (Hyderabad),
                16(2):182-199.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Nadvi1942c">Nadvi, S. S. 1942. “Arab Navigation.” Islamic Culture (Hyderabad)
                16(4):404-423.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Naro1978">Naro, A. J. 1978. “A Study on the Origins of Pidginization.” Language 54:
                314-347.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Neumann1980a">Neumann, G. 1980 “Kleinasien,” in Neumann, G., and J. Unterman, eds. 1980. Die
                Sprachen im Römischen Reich der Kaiserzeit 167-185.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Neumann1980b">Neumann, G., and J. Unterman, eds. 1980. Die Sprachen im Römischen Reich der
                Kaiserzeit. Cologne: Bonn.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Nibbi1975">Nibbi, A. 1975. The Sea Peoples and Egypt. Park Ridge: Noyes Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Niccolo1544">Niccolo, P. T., 1544. Istruzione sul Modo di Fabbricar le Galee: MS It. IV Cod.
                26. Venice: Biblioteca Marciana.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Nicol1988">Nicol, D. M. 1988. Byzantium &amp; Venice. Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Nicolas1961">Nicolas, L. 1961. Histoire de la Marine Française. Paris: Presses Universitaires
                de France.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Niermeyer1976">Niermeyer, F. 1954-1976. Mediae Latinitatis Lexicon Minus. Leiden.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Niermeyer1982">Niermeyer, H. G., ed. 1982. Phönizoer im Westen. Mainz: Madrider Beiträge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Noonan1973">Noonan, T. S. 1973. “The Grain Trade of the Northern Black Sea in Antiquity.”
                American Journal of Philology 94: 231-242.</bibl>
            <bibl>Nordenskiöld, A. E. 1887. Periplus. Stockholm. Nougayrol, R. 1960. “Nouveaux
                Textes Accadiens de Ras-Shamra.” Comptes Rendus des Séances de l’Académie des
                Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres 104:163-171.,</bibl>
            <bibl>Oelschläger, V. R. B. 1940. A Medieval Spanish Word-List: A Preliminary Dated
                Vocabulary of First Appearances up to Berceo. Madison: University of Wisconsin
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Öhmann, E. 1940. “Zum Sprachlichen Einfluss Italiens Auf Deutschland II: Über
                Einige Mhd: Ausdrücke Der Seefahrt.” Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 41:
                145-156.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Oikonomides1995">Oikonomides, A. N., ed. 1995. Hanno the Carthaginian: Periplus or Circumnavigation
                (of Africa). Chicago: Ares Publishers, Inc.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Oleson1986">Oleson, J. P. 1986. Bronze Age Greek and Roman Technology: A Select Annotated
                Bibliography. New York: Garland Publishing, Inc.</bibl>
            <bibl>Del Olmo Lete, G. 1981. Mitos y Legendas de Canaan Según la Tradición de Ugarit.
                Madrid: Cristiandad.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Onions1969">Onions, C.T. 1969. The Oxford Dictionary of English Etymology. Oxford University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Oppenheim1954">Oppenheim, A. 1954. “The Seafaring Merchants of Ur.” Journal of the American
                Oriental Society 74: 6-17.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Oppenheim1973">Oppenheim, A. L. 1973. “Towards a History of Glass in the Ancient Near East.”
                Journal of the American Oriental Society 93: 259-266.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ormerod1924">Ormerod, H. A. 1924. Piracy in the Ancient World. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ortelius1570">Ortelius, A. (compiler) 1570. Theatrum Orbis Terraraum, in Volume III of the First
                Series of Theatrum Orbis Terrarum: A Series of Atlases in Facsimile. Antwerp.</bibl>
            <bibl>O'Scanlan, T. 1831. Diccionario Marítimo Español: Que Además de las Definiciones
                de las Voces con Sus Equivalentes en Francés, Inglés e Italiano. Madrid: Imprenta
                Real.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ostrogorsky1969">Ostrogorsky, G. 1969. History of the Byzantine State. New Brunswick: Rutgers
                University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Paasch1908">Paasch, H. 1908. Dictionnaire de Marine
                Anglais-Français-Allemand-Espagnol-Italien. Paris: Librairie Maritime et
                Coloniale.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Palacio, D. G. 1944. Instrucción Nautica para Navegar. Madrid: Ediciones
                Cultura Hispanica, Collecion de Incunables Americanos, VIII.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Palmer1954">Palmer, L. R. 1954. The Latin Language. London: Faber &amp; Faber.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Palmer1980">Palmer, L. R. 1980. The Greek Language. Atlantic Heights, New Jersey: Humanities
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Panciera1956">Panciera, S. 1956. “Liburna.” Epigraphica 18: 130-156.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Panshin1950">Panshin, A. J., et al. 1950. Forest Products. 1st ed. New York:
                McGraw-Hill.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Panshin1962">Panshin, A. J., et al. 1962. Forest Products: Their Sources, Production, and
                Utilization. 2nd ed. New York: McGraw-Hill.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pantera1614">Pantera, P. 1614. L'Armata Navale del Capitan Pantero Pantera. Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Papadopoulos1580">Papadopoulos, S. A. 1972. The Greek Merchant Marine: 1453-1580. Athens: National
                Bank of Greece.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pardee2106">Pardee, D. 1975. “The Ugaritic Text 2106: 10-18: A Bottomoy Loan?” Journal of
                American Oriental Society 95: 612-619.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pardessus1845">Pardessus, J. M. 1828-1845. Collection de Lois Maritimes Antérieures au XVIII
                Siècle. 6 vols. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Parker1984">Parker, A. J. 1984. “Shipwrecks and Ancient Trade in the Mediterranean.”
                Archaeological Review of Cambridge 3(2):99-113.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Paviot1989">Paviot, J., and E. Rieth. 1988-1989. “Un Compte de Construction de Caravelles
                Portugaises à Bruxelles en 1438-1459.” O Arquéologo Português,
                IV(6/7):307-331.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Peachey1990">Peachey, C. 1990. “Model Building in Nautical Archaeology.” Biblical Archaeologist
                53 (1): 46-54.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pegolotti1340">Pegolotti, F. B., and A. Evans, ed. 1310-1340. La Practica della Mercatura.
                Cambridge: Medieval Academy of America.</bibl>
            <bibl>Peláez, M. J., ed. 1987. Derecho de la Navegación en Europa: Homenaje a F. Valls i
                Taberner. Barcelona.</bibl>
            <bibl>Peláez, M. J. 1987. “Cónsules Náuticos y Cónsules de Mar y de Agua Dulce.
                Instituciones de Derecho Comercial y Marítimo Histórico Catalán, Francés e Italiano.
                Teoría General del Consulado Marítimo,” in Peláez, ed., Derecho de la Navegación en
                Europa: Homenaje a F. Valls i Taberner, 1727-1774.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pellegrini1979">Pellegrini, G. B. 1979. “Introduzione alla Toponomastica,” in Cortelazzo, ed.
                Guida ai Dialetti Veneti. Cooperativa Libraria Editrice Degli Studenti
                dell'Università di Padova.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Peretti1979">Peretti, A. 1979. Il Periplo di Scilace: Studio sul Primo Portolano del
                Mediterraneo. Pisa: Giardini.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pennell1989">Pennell, C. R. 1989. Piracy and Diplomacy in Seventeenth Century North Africa: the
                Journal of Thomas Baker, English Consul in Tripoli, 1677-1685. Fairleigh Dickinson
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Pérez-Embid, F. 1969. “Navigation et Commerce dans le port de Séville au Bas Moyen
                Âge.” Le Moyen Âge 1: 263-289, 479-502.</bibl>
            <bibl>Pérez-Embid, F., and F. Padrón. 1970. Bibliografía Española de la Historia
                Marítima (1932-1962). Seville.</bibl>
            <bibl>Perrone Mercanti, M. 1979. Ancorae Antiquae: Per Una Cronologia Preliminare dell
                Ancore del Mediterraneo. Rome: L’Erma di Bretschneider.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pernoud1949">Pernoud, R., ed. 1949. Les Statuts Municipaux de Marseille: Collection de Textes
                pour Servir à l'Histoire de Provence. Monaco: Archives du Palais.</bibl>
            <bibl>Peterson Ekenberger, J. 1977. “The Mediterranean, A Special Issue.” Ambio 6:
                299-376.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pharr1952">Pharr, C., translat. 1952. Codex Theodosianus. Princeton University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Phillips1986">Phillips, C. R. 1986. Six Galleons for the King of Spain. Baltimore: Johns
                Hopkins University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Phillips1634">Phillips, C. R. 1990. Los Tres Reyes 1628-1634. Minneapolis: University of
                Minnesota Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Phillips1994">Phillips, C. R. 1994. “The Carabel and the Galleon,” in Cogs, Caravels and
                Galleons - The Sailing Ship 1000-1650, 91-114.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Picchi1980">Picchi, F.A. 1980 A practical guide for mariners English-Italian: New York, French
                &amp; European Publishing.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pierce1971">Pierce, R. H. 1971. “Egyptian Loan-Words in Ancient Greek.” Symbolae Osloenses
                46(1): 96-107.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Piloti1420">Piloti, E. 1420. Traité d’Emmanuel Piloti sur le Passage en Terre Sainte.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Piloti1958">Piloti, E., and P. H. Dopp, ed. 1958. Traité d’Emmanuel Piloti sur le Passage en
                Terre Sainte. Louvain: Publications de l'Université Lovanium de Léopoldville.
                Pirenne, H. 1936. Economic and Social History of Medieval Europe. London, Routledge
                &amp; Kegan Paul Limited.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pirenne1939">Pirenne, H. 1939. Mohammed and Charlemagne. London: George Allen &amp; Unwin,
                Limited.</bibl>
            <bibl>Pliny the Elder. Historia Naturalis. Cambridge, Harvard University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pollux1900">Pollux, Julius (Grammaticus), and E. Bethe, ed. 1900. Onomasticon: Vol. I:
                Lexicographi Graeci 9.1. Leipzig: Teubner.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pollux1931">Pollux, Julius (Grammaticus), and E. Bethe, ed. 1931. Onomasticon: Vol. II:
                Lexicographi Graeci 9.2. Leipzig: Teubner.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Polunin1985">Polunin, O., and M. A. Walters. 1985. A Guide to the Vegetation of Britain and
                Europe. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pomey1978">Pomey, P., and A. Tchernia. 1978. `”Le Tonnage Maximum des Navires de Commerce
                Romains.” Archaeonautica 2: 233-251.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pontillo1975">Pontillo, J. J. 1975. “Nautical Terms in Sixteenth Century American Spanish.” PhD.
                diss., State Univeristy of New York, Buffalo.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Popham1983">Popham, M., et al. 1983. “Euboean Exports to Al Mina, Cyprus and Crete: A
                Reassessment.” British School at Athens 78:281-290.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pounds1974">Pounds, N. J. 1974. An Economic History of Medieval Europe. Longman.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pounds1978">Pounds, N. J. 1978. An Historical Geography of Medieval Europe, 450 B.C - A.D.
                1330. Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Prati1951">Prati, A. 1951. Vocabolario Etimologico Italiano. Turin.</bibl>
            <bibl>Procopius. History of the Wars. 5 vols. Harvard University Press, Loeb
                Library.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pryor1981">Pryor, J. H. 1981. Business Contracts of Medieval Provence: Selected Notulæ from
                the Cartulary of Giraud Amalric of Marseilles, 1248. Toronto.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pryor1983">Pryor, J. H. 1983. “The Naval Battles of Roger of Lauria.” Journal of Medieval
                History 9: 179-216.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pryor1984">Pryor, J. H. 1984. “The Naval Architecture of Crusader Transport Ships: A
                Reconstruction of Some Archetypes for Round-Hulled Sailing Vessels.” Mariner's
                Mirror 70: 171-219, 275-292, 363-386.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pryor1216">Pryor, J. H. 1987. “The Voyage of Jacques de Vitry from Genoa to Acre, 1216:
                Juridical and Economic Problems in Medieval Navigation,” in Peláez, ed., p.
                1689-1714.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pryor1987">Pryor, J. H. 1987. Commerce, Shipping, and Naval Warfare in the Medieval
                Mediterranean. Variorum.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pryor1988">Pryor, J. H. 1988. Geography, Technology, and War: Studies in the Maritime History
                of the Mediterranean, 649-1571. Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pryor1994">Pryor, J. H. 1994. “The Mediterranean Round Ship,” in Unger, ed. Cogs, Caravels
                and Galleons - The Sailing Ship 1000-1650, 59-76.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pryor1990">Pryor, J. H., and S. Bellabarba. 1990. “The Medieval Muslim Ships of the Pisan
                Bacini'.” Mariner's Mirror 76: 99-113.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pulak1985">Pulak, C. 1988. “The Bronze Age Shipwreck at Ulu Burun, Turkey: 1985 Campaign.”
                American Journal of Archaeology 92:1-37.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Pulak1989">Pulak, C., and R. F. Townsend. 1989. “The Hellenistic Shipwreck at Serce Limani,
                Turkey: Preliminary Report.” American Journal of Archaeology 91: 31-58.</bibl>
            <bibl>Quézel, P. 1976. “Les forêts du pourtour méditerranéen.” In Forêts et maquis
                méditerranéens: écologie, conservation et aménagement. Notes techniques du MAB 2,
                9-33. Paris: Les Presses de l’UNESCO.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rabin1984">Rabin, A. 1984. “The Thera Ships: Another Interpretation.” American Journal of
                Archaeology 88:11-19.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rabin1976">Rabin, C. 1976. “Hebrew and Aramaic in the First Century,” in Safrai, S., and M.
                Stern, eds., The Jewish People in the First Century,1007-1039. Philadelphia:
                Fortress Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ragostam1981">Ragostam, R., ed. 1981. Le Genti del Mare Mediterraneo. 2 vols. Naples:
                Bibliotecca di Storia Economica 5.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rainey1970">Rainey, A. F. 1970. El Amarna Tablets. Neukirchen-Vluyn.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ramberti1541">Ramberti, B. 1541. Delle Cose de Turchi: Libri Tre. Venice: Bernardin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ramusio1613">Ramusio, G. B. 1559, 1613. Delle Navigationi et Viaggi: 3 vols. Venice.</bibl>
            <bibl>Real Academia Española. 1970. Diccionario de la Lengua Española. Madrid.</bibl>
            <bibl>Reale Academia d'Italia. 1937. Dizionario di Marina Medievale e Moderno.
                Rome.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Reed1984">Reed, C. M. 1984. “Maritime Traders in the Archaic Greek World.” The Ancient World
                X(1-2):31-43.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Reed2003">Reed, C. M. 2003. Maritime Traders in the Ancient Greek World. Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Reinecke1964">Reinecke, J. 1938 (1964). “Trade Jargons and Creole Dialects as Marginal
                Languages,” in D. Hymes, ed., Language in Culture and Society, 534-546. New York:
                Harper &amp; Row.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Reiske1829">Reiske, I. I., ed. 1829. De Cærimoniis [of Constantine VII Porphyrogenitus]. 2
                vols. Bonn University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Renfrew1987">Renfrew, C. 1987. Archaeology and Language- The Puzzle of Indo-European Origins.
                New York: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Renouard1955">Renouard, Y. 1955. “Mercati e Mercanti Veneziani alla Fine del Duecento,” in La
                Civiltà Veneziana del Secolo di Marco Polo, 83-108. Florence.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Reyerson1978">Reyerson, K. 1978. “Monpellier and the Byzantine Empire: Commerical Interaction in
                the Mediterranean World Before 1350.” Byzantion 48:456-476.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Richard1976">Richard, J. 1976. Orient et Occident au Moyen Ȃge: Contacts et Relations. London:
                Variorum Press, Collected Studies Series.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rickman1971">Rickman, G. E. 1971. Roman Granaries and Store Buildings. Cambridge University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rickman1980">Rickman, G. .E. 1980. The Corn Supply of Ancient Rome. Oxford University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rikli1948">Rikli, M. 1943-1948. Das Pflanzenkleid der Mittelmeerlanden. 3 vols. Bern.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rival1991">Rival, M. 1991. La Charpenterie Navale Romaine: Materiaux, Méthodes, Moyens.
                Paris: Editions du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Robertson1975">Robertson, N. 1975. The Archaeology of Cyprus: Recent Developments. Park Ridge,
                New Jersey: Noyes Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Robson1344">Robson, J. A. 1959. “The Catalan Fleet and Moorish Sea Power (1337-1344).” English
                Historical Review 74: 386-408.</bibl>
            <bibl>della Rocca, et al., eds. 1940. Documenti del Commercio Veneziano nel Secoli
                XI-XIII. 2 vols. Rome/Turin: Sede delli Instituto e Libraria Italiana.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Rodgers1940">Rodgers, W. L. 1967 (1940). Naval Warfare under Oars: Fourth to Sixteenth
                Centuries. Annapolis: U. S. Naval Institute.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Roebuck1950">Roebuck, C. A. 1950. ”The Grain Trade Between Greece and Egypt.” Classical
                Philology 45: 236-247.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rohe1934">Rohe, A. 1934. Die Terminologie der Fischersprache von Grau d'Agde. Lipsia.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Rohlfs1969">Rohlfs, G. 1966-1969. Grammatica Storica della Lingua Italiana e dei Suoi
                Dialetti. 3 vols. Turin: Einaudi.</bibl>
            <bibl>Röllig, W. 1980. “Das Punische im Römischen Reich,” in Neumann, G., and J.
                Untermann, eds., Die Sprachen im Römischen Reich der Kaiserzeit, 285-300. Cologne:
                Bonn.</bibl>
            <bibl>de la Roncière, C. 1909-1932. Histoire de la Marine Française. 3d ed., 5 vols.
                Paris. Rosamani, E. 1958. Vocabolario Giuliano dei Dialetti Parlati nella Regione
                Giuliano-Dalmata. Bologna: Cappelli.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rosamani1975">Rosamani, E., and M. Dario, ed. 1975. Vocabolario Marinaresco Giuliano-Dalmata.
                Florence: Olschki.</bibl>
            <bibl>Rosén, H. B. 1980. “Die Sprachsituation im Römischen Palästina,” in Neumann &amp;
                Untermann, 215-240.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rost1968">Rost, G. A. 1968. Seewesen und Seehandel in der Antike. Amsterdam.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rostaing1974">Rostaing, C. 1974. Les Noms de Lieux. Paris: Presses Universitaires de
                France.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rostovtzeff1906">Rostovtzeff, M. 1906. “Kornerhebung und Transport im Griechisch-Römischen
                Ägypten.” Archiv für Papyrusforschung 3: 201.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rostovtzeff1930">Rostovtzeff, M. 1930. “Rhodes, Delos, and Hellenistic Commerce.” Cambridge Ancient
                History VIII: 618-667.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rostovtzeff1932">Rostovtzeff, M. 1932. “Foreign Commerce in Ptolemic Egypt.” Journal of Economic
                and Business History, III: 728.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rostovtzeff1957">Rostovtzeff, M. 1957. The Social and Economic History of the Roman Empire. 2d. ed.
                Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Rougé, J. 1961. “Quelques Aspects de la Navigation en Méditerranée au Ve Siècle et
                dans la Première Moitié du Vie Siècle.” Cahiers d'Histoire 6: 129-154.</bibl>
            <bibl>Rougé, J. 1966. Recherches sur l'Organisation du Commerce Maritime en Méditerranée
                sous l'Empire Romain. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl>Rougé, J.1976. “Ankoina-Anquina.” Revue de Philologie 50: 213-220.</bibl>
            <bibl>Rougé, J. 1981. Ships and Fleets in the Ancient Mediterranean. Wesleyan University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Rowland1984">Rowland, R. J. J. 1984. “The Case of the Missing Sardinian Grain.” The Ancient World, X(1-2): 45-48.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Safrai1976a">Safrai, S., et al. 1976. “The Social and Economic Status of the Jews in the
                Diaspora.” In The Jewish People in the First Century, Volume 2, 701-27. Leiden:
                Brill.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Safrai1976b">Safrai, S., and M. Stern., eds. 1976. The Jewish People in the First Century. 2 vols. Philadelphia: Fortress Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Saggs1989">Saggs, H. W. F. 1989. Civilization Before Greece and Rome. Yale University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Saint Denis, E. 1935. Le Vocabulaire des Manoeuvres Nautiques en Latin. Mâcon:
                Protat Frères.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Saint Denis, E. 197. “Les Types de Navires dans l'Antiquité Gréco-Romaine.”
                Revue de Philologie, de Littérature et d'Histoire Anciennes 48: 10-25.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Salonen1939">Salonen, A. 1939. “Die Wasserfahrzeuge in Babylonien.” Studia Orientalia VIII(4). Helsinki.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Salonen1942">Salonen, A. 1942. “Nautica Babyloniaca.” Studia Orientalia XI(1), 1-118.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Sampson1980">Sampson, R. 1980. Early Romance Texts: an Anthology. Cambridge University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Sandahl1951">Sandahl, B. 1951. “Middle English Sea-Terms.” Essays and Studies on English
                Language and Literature 8. Uppsala: Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Sandars1978">Sandars, N. K. 1978. The Sea Peoples: Warriors of the Ancient Mediterranean
                1250-1150 BC. London: Thames &amp; Hudson.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Sanz1977">Sanz, A. G. 1977. Historia de la Marina de Catalonia. Barcelona.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Sasson1966">Sasson, J. 1966. “Canaanite Maritime Involvement in the Second Millennium B. C.” Journal of the American Oriental Society 86: 126-138.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Sayous1988">Sayous, A. E., and M. Steele, ed. 1988. Commerce et Finance en Méditerranée au Moyen Ȃge. Variorum Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Scammel1981">Scammel, G. V. 1981. The World Encompassed: The First European Maritime Empires, c. 800-1650. Berkeley: Univeristy of California.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Scandurra1972">Scandurra, E. 1972. “The Maritime Republics: Medieval and Renaissance Ships in Italy,” in G. Bass, ed.: 205-224.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Schiaffini1929">Schiaffini, A. 1929. Il Mercante Genovese nel Medio Evo e Il suo Linguaggio. Genoa.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Schiaffini1930">Schiaffini, A. 1930. “Profilo Storico della Lingua Commerciale dai Primordi di Roma all'Età Moderna. I: Roma e i Regni Romano-Barbarici.” Italia Dialettale 6:
                1-56.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Schmidt1862">Schmidt, M., ed. 1862. Lexicon (of Hesychius). Jena.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Schmitt1904">Schmitt, J., trans. 1904. The Chronicle of Morea. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Schoff1912">Schoff, W. H., ed. 1912 The Periplus of the Erythraean Sea. London: Longmans, Green, &amp; Co.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Schoff1913">Schoff, W. H., trans. 1913. The Periplus of Hanno. The Commercial Museum.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Schuchardt1909">Schuchardt, H. 1909. “Die Lingua Franca.” Zeitschrift für Philologie 33:
                441-461.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Schuchardt1980">Schuchardt, H., and G. G. Gilbert, ed. 1980. Pidgin and Creole Languages: Selected
                Essays by Hugo Schuchardt. Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Schultz1970">Schultz, C. R. 1970. Bibliography of Maritime and Naval History Periodical
                Articles. Texas A&amp;M Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Scott1932">Scott, P., translat. 1932. Codex Justinianus. Cincinnati.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Scottas1938">Scottas, J. 1938. Messageries Maritimes de Venise XIVe et XVe Siècles. Paris:
                Société d'Editions Géographiques, Maritimes et Coloniales.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Seager1966">Seager, R. 1966. “Lysias Againts the Corndealers.” Historia 15: 172-184.</bibl>
            <bibl>Sebeok, T. A., ed. Current Trends in Linguistics. 6 vols. The Hague: Mouton &amp;
                Company.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Segert1976">Segert, S. 1976. A Grammar of Phoenician and Punic. Munich: C. H. Beck.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Segert1985">Segert, S. 1985. A Basic Grammar of the Ugaritic Language: with Selected Texts and
                Glossary. University of California Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Servion1465">Servion, J. 1464-1465. Chroniques de Savoye: MHP III, Scriptores I.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Setton1975">Setton, K. M. 1975. “Catalan Society in Greece in the Fourteenth Century,” in
                Essays in Memory of Basil Laourdas,p. 241-284. Thessaloniki.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Setton1571">Setton, K. M. 1976-1978. The Papacy and the Levant, 1204-1571. 2 vols. American
                Philosophical Society.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Setton1974">Setton, K. M. 1974. Europe and the Levant in the Middle Ages and Renaissance.
                London: Variorum Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Severin1982">Severin, T. 1982. The Sinbad Voyage. New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons.</bibl>
            <bibl>Shahîd, I. 1984. Rome and the Arabs. Washington D.C., Dumbarton Oaks Research
                Library and Collection.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Shaw1972">Shaw, J. W. 1972 “Greek and Roman Harbour Works,” in G. Bass, ed., 87-112.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Shaw1989">Shaw, J. W. 1989. “Phoenicians in Southern Crete.” American Journal of Archaeology
                93: 165-183.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Shennum1977">Shennum, D. 1977. English-Egyptian Index of Faulkner’s Concise Dictionary of
                Middle Egyptian. Undena Publishing.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Simpson1989">Simpson, J. A., and E. S. C. Weiner, eds. 1989. The Oxford English Dictionary. 2d.
                ed. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Singer1958">Singer, C. 1958. From Magic to Science. New York: Dover Publications.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Skok1937">Skok, P. 1926-1937. “Zum Balkanlatein.” Zeitschrift für Romanische Philologie 46:
                385-410 (1926); 48: 398-413 (1928); 50: 484-532 (1930); 54: 175-215 (1934); 54:
                424-499 (1934); 57: 462-480 (1937).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Skok1933">Skok, P. 1933. Nasa Pomorska i Ribarska Terminologija na Jadranu. Jadranska
                Straža.</bibl>
            <bibl>Skržinskaya, E. C. 1968. “Storia della Tana.” Studi Veneziani 10: 3-46.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Smith1626">Smith, J. 1626. “An Accidence for Young Seamen,” in E. Arber, ed., Travels and
                works of Captain John Smith, 787-804. Edinburgh.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Smith1627">Smith, J. 1627. A Sea Grammar. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Smith1984">Smith, N. B., and T. G. Bergin. 1984. An Old Provençal Primer. New York,
                Garland.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Smith1993">Smith, R. C. 1993. Vanguard of Empire: Ships of Exploration in the Age of
                Columbus. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Snodgrass1980">Snodgrass, A. 1980. Archaic Greece: The Age of Experiment. Berkeley: University of
                California Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Solin1980">Solin, H. 1980. “Juden und Syrer im Römischen Reich,” in Neumann, G., and J.
                Untermann, eds., Die Sprachen im Römischen Reich der Kaiserzeit, 301-330. Cologne:
                Bonn.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Sophocles1870">Sophocles, E. A. 1870. Greek Lexicon of the Roman and Byzantine Periods.
                Boston.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Sosson1962">Sosson, J. B. 1962. “Un Compt Inédit de Construction de Galères à Narbonne
                (1318-1320).” Bulletin de l'Institut Historique Belge de Rome 34: 57-317.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Soucek1975">Soucek, S. 1975. “Certain Types of Ships in Ottoman Turkish Terminology.” Turcica
                233-244.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Souter1964">Souter, A. 1964. A Glossary of Later Latin. Oxford.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Speiser1936">Speiser, E. A. 1936. “The Name Phoinikes.” Language 12: 124-125.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Starr1960">Starr, C. G. 1960. The Roman Imperial Navy 31 B.C.-A.D.324. Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Starr1977">Starr, C. G. 1977. Economic and Social Growth of Early Greece 800-500 B. C. New
                York.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Starr1982">Starr, C. A. 1982. “Economic and Social Conditions in the Greek World.” Cambridge
                Ancient History 3: 417-441.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Starr1989">Starr, C. A. 1989. The Influence of Sea Power on Ancient History. Oxford
                University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Steffy1981">Steffy, J. R. 1981. “The Medieval Cargo Ship: Evidence from Nautical Archaeology,”
                in Symonds, ed., 13-19.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Steffy1983">Steffy, J. R. 1983. “The Athlit Ram: A Preliminary Investigation of Its
                Structure.” Mariner’s Mirror 69: 229-247.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Steffy1985">Steffy, J. R. 1985. “The Kyrenia Ship: an Interim Report on its Hull
                Construction.” American Journal of Archaeology 89:71-101.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Steffy1994">Steffy, J. R. 1994. Wooden Shipbuilding and the Interpretation of Shipwrecks.
                Texas A&amp;M University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Strabo1932">Strabo, and H. L. Jones, trans. 1932. Geography. 8 vols. London: William Heinemann
                (Loeb).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Stoianovich1992">Stoianovich, T. 1992. Between East and West: The Balkan and Mediterranean Worlds”
                Economies and Societies: Traders, Towns, and Households. Caratzas.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Stuard1992">Stuard, Susan Mosher 1992 A state of deference: Ragusa/Dubrovnik in the medieval
                centuries: Philadelphia, Univ. of Pennsylvania Press (AHpc partial)</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Stussi1967">Stussi, A., ed. 1967. Zibaldone da Canal: Manoscritto Mercantile del Sec. XIV.
                Venice, Comitato per la Pubblicazione delle Fonti Relative alla Storia di
                Venezia.</bibl>
            <bibl>Suarez Gil, L. 1983 Diccionario técnico marítimo Ingles-Español-Ingles: New York,
                French &amp; European</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Susmel1956">Susmel, L. 1956. “Tecnica dei Veneziani nei Boschi di Rovere.” Monti Boschi 7:
                212-222.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Symonds1973">Symonds, C. L. 1973. “Jal's Nef X and Genoese Naval Architecture in the 13th
                Century.” Mariner's Mirror 59: 161-170.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Symonds1981">Symonds, C. L., ed. 1981. New Aspects of Naval History: Selected Papers Presented
                at the Fourth Naval History Symposium. Annapolis: Naval Institute Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Syria, P. 1602. Arte de la Verdadera Navegacion.Valencia: Juan Chysostomo
                Garriz.</bibl>
            <bibl>Szemerenyi, O. “The Origins of the Greek Lexicon: Ex Oriente Lux.” Journal of
                Hellenic Studies 94:144-157.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Szemerenyi1986">Szemerenyi, O. J. L. 1986. “Etyma Graeca V (30-32): Vocabula Maritima Tria,” in
                Festschrift für Ernst Risch zum 75. Berlin: de Gruyter.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tafel1857">Tafel, G.L.Fr., and G. M. Thomas. 1856-1857. Urkunden Zur Älteren Handels: und
                Staatsgeschichte der Republik Venedig mit Besonderer Bezeichnung auf Bysanz und die
                Levante. 3 vols. Vienna, Fontes Rerum Austriacarum, Zweite Abteilung, Diplomataria
                et Acta, 12-14.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tangheroni1978">Tangheroni, M., and L. diNero. 1978. Commercio e Navigazione nel Mediterraneo
                Medievale. Rome: Scholastica.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tasca1606">Tasca, G. P. 1606. Relatione del Viaggio d’Alessandria d’Egitto.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Taylor1971">Taylor, E. G. R. 1971. The Haven-Finding Art: a History of Navigation from
                Odysseus to Captain Cook. New York, American Elsevier Publishing Company.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tchernia1978">Tchernia, A., et al. 1978. L'Épave Romaine de la Madrague de Giens: XXXIVe
                Supplément à Gallia. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Teal1025">Teal, J. L. 1959. “The Grain Supply of the Byzantine Empire, 330-1025.” Dumbarton
                Oaks Papers 13: 87-139.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Teixidor1975">Teixidor, J. 1975. “Early Phoenician Presence in Cyprus: Analysis of Epigraphical
                Material,” in Robertson, N., ed., 121-128.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tenenti1962">Tenenti, A. 1962. Cristoforo da Canal: La Marine Vénitienne Avant Lépante.
                Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Terlingen1943">Terlingen, J. H. 1943. Los Italianismos en Español Desde la Formación del Idioma
                Hasta Principios del Siglo XVII. Amsterdam.,</bibl>
            <bibl> Theophrastus. 1916. Enquiry into Plants. 2 vols. New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons
                (Loeb Library).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Thirgood1981">Thirgood, J. V. 1981. Man and the Mediterranean Forest: A History of Resource
                Depletion. London: Academic Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Thiriet1954">Thiriet, F. 1954. “Les Chroniques Vénitiennes de la Marcienne et leur Importance
                pour l’Histoire de la Romaine Gréco-Vénitienne.” Mélanges de l’Ecole Française de
                Rome 66: 241-292.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Thiriet1959">Thiriet, F. 1959 La Romanie Vénitienne au Moyen Âge. Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Thiriet1977">Thiriet, F. 1977. Études sur la Romanie Gréco-Vénitienne (Xe-XVe siécles). London,
                Variorum Reprints, Collected Studies Series 60.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Thompson1983">Thompson, D. J. 1983. “Nile Grain Transport under the Ptolemies,” in Garnsey et
                al., p. 64-75.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Thompson1300">Thompson, J. W. 1928/ Economic and Social History of the Middle Ages (300-1300). 2
                vols. New York: Frederick Ungar Publishing Company.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Thompson1931">Thompson, J. W. 1931. Economic and Social History of Europe in the Later Middle
                Ages (1300-1530). New York: Appleton-Century.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Thompson1937">Thompson, J. W., and E. N. Johnson. 1937. An Introduction to Medieval Europe
                300-1500. New York: W.W. Norton.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Throckmorton1972">Throckmorton, P. 1972. “Romans on the Sea,” in G. Bass, ed., p. 65-86.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Throckmorton1987">Throckmorton, P., ed. 1987. The Sea Remembers. New York: Weidenfeld &amp;
                Nicolson.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Thumb1898">Thumb, A. 1898. “Zur Geschichte des Griechischen Digamma.” Indogermanische
                Forschungen Anzeige 1: 294-342., ,</bibl>
            <bibl> Thür, G. 1987. “Hypotheken-Urkunde eines Seedarlehens für eine Reise nach Muziris
                und Apographe für die Tetarte in Alexandria (zu P. Vindob. G. 40.822).” Tyche 2:
                229-245.</bibl>
            <bibl>Thureau-Dangin, F. 1931. “Vocabulaires de Ras Shamra.” Syria 12(5):
                228-230.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Thylander1952">Thylander, H. 1952. Étude sur l'Épigraphie Latine. 8 vols. Lund: Acta Instituti
                Regni Sueciae, Series 5.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tigay1982">Tigay, J. H. 1982. The Evolution of the Gilgamesh Epic. Philadelphia: University
                of Pennsylvania Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tomback1978">Tomback, R. S. 1978. Comparative Semitic Lexicon of the Phoenician and Punic
                Languages. Missoula: Scholars Press for the Society of Biblical Literature.</bibl>
            <bibl>Topham-Meekings, D. 1976. The Hollow Ships: Trade and Seafaring in the Ancient
                World. London: MacMillan.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Topping1977">Topping, P. 1977. “Co-existence of Greeks and Latins in Frankish Morea and
                Venetian Crete,” in Studies on Latin Greece, AD 1205-1715, No. 11. London: Variorum
                Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Torr1964">Torr, C. 1964. Ancient Ships. Chicago.</bibl>
            <bibl>Torres Balbás, L. 1946. “Atarazanas Hispanomusulmanas.” Al-Andalus 9(1):
                175-209.</bibl>
            <bibl>Torres Balbás, L. 1946. “Las Alhóndigas Hispanomusulmanas y el Corral del Carbón
                de Granada.” Al-Andalus 11(2): 447-480.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Torsello1972">Torsello, M. S. 1972. Liber Secretorum Fidelium Crucis Super Terrae Sanctae
                Recuperatione et Conservatione. Jerusalem.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tovar1980">Tovar, A. 1980. “Das Vulgarlatein in den Provinzen,” in Neumann &amp; Untermann,
                331-342.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Toynbee1973">Toynbee, A. 1973. Constantine Porphyrogenitus and His World. London.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Triantaphyllides1909">Triantaphyllides, M. 1909. Die Lehnwörter der Mittelgriechischen Vulgarliteratur.
                Strassburg.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tucci1973">Tucci, U. 1973. “La Navigazione Veneziana nel Duecento e nel Primo Trecento,” in
                Venezia e il Levante Fino al Secolo XV. Florence.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tucci1986">Tucci, U. 1986. “Architettura Navale Veneziana Misure di Vascelli nella Secondo
                Metà del Cinquecento.” Bolletino dell’Atlante Linguistico Mediterranean 5-6.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Turner1971">Turner, E. G. 1971. Greek Manuscripts of the Ancient World. Oxford University
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Turner1980">Turner, E. G. 1980. Greek Papyri: An Introduction. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Twiss1876">Twiss, T., ed. 1871-1876. The Black Book of the Admiralty. 6 vols. London: Series
                Monumenta Juridica of Rerum Britannicarum Medii Aevi Scriptores.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tzalas1989">Tzalas, H. E. 1989. Proceedings: 1st International Symposium on Ship Construction
                in Antiquity, Piraeus 1985. Athens.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Unger1600">Unger, R.W. 1980. The Ship in the Medieval Economy. 600-1600. Montreal:
                McGill-Queen’s University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Unger1650">Unger, R.W., ed. 1994. Cogs, Caravels and Galleons - The Sailing Ship 1000-1650.
                London: Conway Maritime.</bibl>
            <bibl>Väänänen, V. 1981 Introduction au latin vulgaire: 3d ed., Paris,
                Klincksieck</bibl>
            <bibl>van Caenegem, R.C., and F. L. Ganshof. 1979. Guide to the Sources of Medieval
                History. Amsterdam: North-Holland Publishing Company.</bibl>
            <bibl>van Doorninck, F. 1972. “Byzantium, Mistress of the Sea 330-641,” in A History of
                Seafaring, edited by G. F. Bass, 133-158.</bibl>
            <bibl>von Konijnenburg, E. 1913. Shipbuilding from Its Beginnings. 3 vols. Brussels:
                Permanent International Association of Congresses of Navigation.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Vasiliev1952">Vasiliev, A. A. 1952. History of the Byzantine Empire. Oxford: Basil
                Blackwell.</bibl>
            <bibl>Vélissaropoulos, J. 1980. Les Nauclères Grecs, Recherches sur Les Institutions en
                Grèce et dans l’Orient Hellénisé. Paris: Librarie Minard.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Vercauteren1925">Vercauteren, F. 1925. “Cataplus et Catabolus.” Bulletin Ducange (Archivum
                latinitatis medii aevi) 2.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Verlinden1970">Verlinden, C. 1970. Le Commerce en Mer Noire des Débuts de l'Époque Byzantine au
                Lendemain de la Conquête de l'Egypt par les Ottomans (1517). Moscow: XIIIe Congrès
                International des Sciences Historiques.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Vidos1939">Vidos, B. E. 1939. Storia delle Parole Marinaresche Italiane Passate in Francese.
                Florence: Biblioteca dell'Archivum Romanicum, 2, vol. 24.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Vidos1965">Vidos, B. E. 1965. Prestito, Espansione e Migrazione dei Termini Technici nelle
                Lingue Romanze e Non Romanze: Problemi, Metodo e Risultati. Florence: Biblioteca
                dell'Archivum Romanicum, 2, vol. 31.,</bibl>
            <bibl> Villain-Gandossi, C. 1978. “Terminologie de l'Appareil de Gouverne (IXe-XVIIIe
                Siècles).” Archæonautica 2: 281-309.</bibl>
            <bibl>Villain-Gandossi, C. 1983. La Méditerranée aux XIIe-XVIe Siècles: Relations
                Maritimes, Diplomatiques et Commerciales. London: Variorum Reprints.</bibl>
            <bibl>Villain-Gandossi, C., et al. 1989. Medieval Ships and the Birth of the
                Technological Sciences. 2 vols. European Coordination Centre for Research and
                Documentation in Social Sciences.</bibl>
            <bibl>Villain-Gandossi, C. 1990. “Les Emprunts de Mots dans la Terminologie Maritime
                Française,” in anon., Navigations et Migrations, p. 101-116.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Villehardouin, G., and J. E. White, Jr., ed. 1968. La Conqueste de
                Constantinople. Appleton Century Crofts.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id=" Vinson1990">Vinson, S. 1990. “Ships in the Ancient Mediterranean.” Biblical Archaeologist
                53(1): 13-18.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Viscidi1944">Viscidi, F. 1944. I Prestiti Latini nel Greco Antico e Bizantino. Padua.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Vitale1951">Vitale, V., ed. 1951. Le Fonti del Diritto Marittima Ligure. Genoa.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Vollers1896">Vollers, K. 1896. “Beiträge zur Kenntnis der Lebenden Arabischen Sprache in
                Aegypten. II. Ueber Lehnwörter. Fremdes und Eigenes.” Zeitschrift Deutschen
                Morgenländischen Gesellschaftt, Pts I-VI, 50: 607-57, Pts. VII-XV: 291-326.</bibl>
            <bibl>von Miklosich, F. 1884-1890. “Die Türkischen Elemente in den Südost- und
                Osteuropäischen Sprachen.” K. Akademie der Wissenschaften,
                Philosophische-historische Classe, Denkschriften 34: 238-338, 35: 105-190, 37: 1-88,
                38: 1-194. Vienna.</bibl>
            <bibl>von Soden, W. 1959-1965. Akkadisches Handwörterbuch. 3 vols. Wiesbaden.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Vorestch1887">Vorestch, K., ed. 1887. Les Gestes des Chiprois, p. p. G. Raynaud. Geneva.</bibl>
            <bibl>de Vries, K., and M. Katzev. 1972. “Greek, Etruscan and Phoenician Ships and
                Shipping,” in A History of Seafaring Based on Underwater Archaeology, edited by G.
                F. Bass, 37-64. London: Walker.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wachsmann1989">Wachsmann, S. 1989. Seagoing Ships and Seamanship in the Late Bronze Age Levant.
                Unpub. PhD. diss. Jerusalem: The Hebrew University.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wachsman1981">Wachsman, S. 1981. “The Ships of the Sea Peoples.” International Journal of
                Nautical Archaeology 11:297-304.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wachsman1984">Wachsman, S. &amp; Raveh, K. 1984. “A Concise Nautical History of Dor/Tantura.”
                International Journal of Nautical Archaeology 13:223-241.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wachsmann1998">Wachsmann, S. 1998. Seagoing Ships and Seamanship in the Late Bronze Age Levant.
                Texas A&amp;M University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wagner1870">Wagner, W. 1870. Medieval Greek Texts: A Collection of the Earliest Compositions
                in Vulgar Greek, Prior to the Year 1500 . Chicago: Argonaut, Inc.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wagner1964">Wagner, M. L. 1960-1964. Des Dizionario Etimologico Sardo. University of Michigan
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Walker1965">Walker, D. S. 1965. The Mediterranean Lands. University of Michigan Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wallinga1964">Wallinga, H. T. 1964. “Nautika (I), the Unit of Capacity for Ancient Ships.
                Mnemosyne 17: 1-40.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Walsh1983">Walsh, T. J. 1983. The Verbal Suffix -idiare: Latin Origin and Romance
                Development. PhD. diss. Berkeley: University of California.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ward1968">Ward, W. A. 1968. The Role of Phoenicians in the Interaction of Mediterranean
                Civilizations. New York: Syracuse University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Warmington1934">Warmington, E. H. 1934. Greek Geography. New York.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Warren1979">Warren, P. 1979. T”he Miniature Fresco from the West House at Akrotiri, Thera, and
                Its Aegean Setting.” Journal of Hellenic Studies 99:115-129.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Waters1967">Waters, D. W. 1967. Rutters of the Sea: The Sailing Directions of Pierre Garcie.
                New Haven.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wehr1976">Wehr, H. 1976. Arabic-English Dictionary. Ithaca: Spoken Language Services.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="West1978">West, M. L. 1978. "Stesichorus at Lille." Zeitschrift für Papyrologie und
                Epigraphik. 29: 1–4.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wheeler1979">Wheeler, T. S., et al. 1979. “Mediterranean Trade in Copper and Tin in the Late
                Bronze Age.” Annali dell’Instituto Italianio di Numismatica 26:139-152.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Whinnom1977">Whinnom, K. 1977. “The Context and Origins of Lingua Franca,” in Meisel, ed.,
                Langues en Contact 3-18.</bibl>
            <bibl>White, D. 1986. “Excavation of Bates’ Island, a Late Bronze Age Egyptian Trading
                Station.” American Journal of Archaeology 90:205-206.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="White1974">White, L., Jr. 1974. “The Diffusion of the Lateen Sail.” Proceedings of the XIII
                International Congress of the History of Science, Sects. iii-iv, p. 212-225.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Whittaker1983">Whittaker, C. R. 1983. “Late Roman Trade and Traders,” in Garnsey et al., eds., p.
                163-180.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wilcken1912">Wilcken, U., et al. 1912. Grundzüge und Chrestomathie der Papyruskunde.
                Leipzig.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wilkins1965">Wilkins, E. H., et al., eds. 1965. A Concordance to the Divine Comedy of Dante
                Alighieri. Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Williams1962">Williams, E. B. 1962. From Latin to Portuguese: Historical Philology and
                Morphology of the Portuguese Language. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylavnia
                Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Winter1954">Winter, H. 1954. “Catalan Portolan Maps and Their Place in the Total View of
                Cartographic Development.” Imago Mundi 11: 1-12.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wise1952">Wise, L. E., &amp; E. C. Jahn. 1952. Wood Chemistry. 2d ed. 2 vols. New York:
                Reinhold: ACS Monograph Series.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wiseman1973">Wiseman, D. J. 1973. Peoples of Old Testament Times. Oxford.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Woodbridge1951">Woodbridge, H. C. 1951. “A Tentative Bibliography of Spanish and Catalan Nautical
                Dictionaries, Glossaries, and Word Lists.” Mariner's Mirror 37: 63-75.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Woodhouse1910">Woodhouse, S. C. 1971 (1910). English-Greek Dictionary: A Vocabulary of the Attic
                Language. Routelege.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Wright1982">Wright, R. 1982. Late Latin and Early Romance in Spain and Carolingian France.
                Liverpool: Francis Cairns.,</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Xanthoudides1939">Xanthoudides, S. 1939. The Venetian Domination in Crete. Athens. (Greek)</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Yannai1983">Yannai, A. 1983. Studies on Trade Between the Levant and the Aegean in the 14th to
                12th Centuries B.C. Dissertation, Linacre College. Oxford.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Yeo1946">Yeo, C. 1946. “Land and Sea Transportation in Imperial Italy.” Transactions of the
                American Philological Association 77: 221-44.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Zeller1910">Zeller, H.L. 1910. Die Assisen von Jerusalem: Sammlung älterer Seerechtsquellen,
                Heft 4, herausg von H.L. Zeller. II Abteil (Mittelalter)</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Zgusta1980">Zgusta, L. 1980. “Die Rolle des Griechischen im römischen Kaiserreich.” In
                Neumann, G., and J. Untermann, eds. 1980. Die Sprachen im Römischen Reich der
                Kaiserzeit. Cologne: Bonn., 121-46. Köln: Rheinland Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Zupko1981">Zupko, R. E. 1981. Italian Weights and Measures from the Middle Ages to the
                Nineteenth Century. Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </standOff>
</TEI>
